<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter of enquiry to the reverend fathers of the Society of Jesus written in the person of a dissatisfied Roman Catholick.</title>
            <author>Taylor, James, fl. 1687-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10414</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13558582</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13558582</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63618)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 803:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter of enquiry to the reverend fathers of the Society of Jesus written in the person of a dissatisfied Roman Catholick.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, James, fl. 1687-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Rogers ... and Samuel Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at the end: A.B.</note>
                  <note>Written by James Taylor.  Cf. BM, NUC pre-1956, Wing.</note>
                  <note>"I who make these enquiries, am a layman of the Church of England ..."--Advertisement.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100283:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100283:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER OF ENQUIRY TO The Reverend Fathers OF THE <hi>Society of Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in the Perſon of a Diſſatisfied</hi> Roman Catholick.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Hen. Wharton, R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> in Chriſto P.ac D.D. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmo Archiep. Cant. a Sacris Domeſt.</signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Octob.</hi> 26. 1688.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet;</hi> and <hi>Samuel Smith</hi> at the <hi>Princes Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:100283:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100283:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>COuld I believe it fit <hi>to Lye for GOD,</hi> or that <hi>Truth</hi> needed the ſervice of <hi>Falſhood,</hi> I might have been tempted to imitate the Tricks and Deceiving Arts of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Factors (for in Charity, we muſt ſuppoſe ſome of them at leaſt, to believe what they ſay to be <hi>Truth,</hi> and that their <hi>Cauſe</hi> is that of <hi>GOD</hi>) and boldly have ſent this <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> abroad, as really writ by a <hi>Romaniſt:</hi> But as I am a Member of a <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe <hi>Superſtructures,</hi> as well as her <hi>Foundation</hi> is the pure <hi>Truth,</hi> (and one that is reſolv'd to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> wherever they lead me) ſo I ſhould think that I deſerv'd the ſevere puniſhment of being depriv'd of the happineſs of her Communion, if I endeavour'd to ſerve her Intereſts by any means ſo contrary to her <hi>Nature and Manner of dealing with Mankind.</hi> But as 'tis no improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuppoſition, that there ſhould be ſome <hi>Diſſatisfied,</hi> or <hi>Doubting,</hi> or <hi>Inquiſitive</hi> Perſon in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion; ſo neither can it. I hope, be injurious or offenſive to any, openly to declare. That I who make theſe <hi>Enquiries,</hi> am a <hi>Layman</hi> of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> and that I make them in the Perſon of a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> is for no other reaſon, but only to preſerve a better <hi>Decorum,</hi> and the more to affect the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for whoſe ſake I chiefly Publiſh this <hi>Letter.</hi> And with all the <hi>Charity and Good-will,</hi> that one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> owes to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I do humbly beſeech every <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves he has a Soul to be ſav'd, and values its Salvation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove being of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Party,</hi> or <hi>ſerving a Cauſe,</hi> or the greateſt <hi>worldly</hi> Intereſt, ſeriouſly for once, to ſuppoſe himſelf
<pb facs="tcp:100283:3"/>this <hi>Diſſatisfied,</hi> or <hi>Doubting,</hi> or <hi>Inquiring</hi> Perſon, and let him in the Name of <hi>GOD</hi> lay his Hand upon his Heart, and conſider whether theſe <hi>Enquiries</hi> are not pertinent and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, and if they be, I beg him impartially, and as he will anſwer it at the Great Day, to weigh the Anſwers that may by his <hi>Party</hi> be return'd to them, whether he be really and fully ſatisfied that they are juſt and rational. I confeſs, <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, Doubting,</hi> and <hi>Inquiſitive</hi> Perſons, cannot be ſo frequent in a <hi>Church,</hi> where they are taught ſolely and <hi>blindly</hi> to rely upon their <hi>Paſtors</hi> and Spiritual <hi>Guides,</hi> and generally ſpeaking do ſo, as in a <hi>Church</hi> which gives a modeſt liberty of <hi>trying the Spirits,</hi> and of examining and enquiring into the reaſon and truth of things. But yet for all that, my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with Perſons of that Communion, is not ſo little, as to ſuffer me to believe, but that there are a great many whoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings are not ſo muffled, nor ſo far enſlav'd, but that ſometimes they entertain ſerious Thoughts, and take a free View of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the nature of it, and reflect with what <hi>artifice and fraud</hi> it is manag'd in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and that they do believe, when they think ſoberly, that the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> is not an effect of <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Folly,</hi> or <hi>Worldly Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> as their crafty deſigning <hi>Prieſts</hi> would perſwade them. This granted me, ſuch Perſons then may reaſonably be preſum'd (that if either they would give themſelves the trouble, or durſt) to think it neceſſary thus to Addreſs themſelves to the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who have aſſum'd to themſelves the Reputation of the beſt <hi>Spiritual Guides.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100283:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Fathers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SINCE 'tis thought by a great many, that you are the only Oracles of Learning and Knowledge of any <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in our <hi>Church,</hi> it will not be wondred at, that I particularly Addreſs this <hi>Letter of Enquiry</hi> to you. <hi>Faith</hi> no more then <hi>Love</hi> can be forc'd, they are both free Agents. I am diſſatisfied, doubt, and am at a ſtand, about ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Points in our Religion. I have a juſt reverence for the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> of our Church, but yet I know <hi>Error</hi> is older than ſhe, and <hi>Truth</hi> than either of them. I have no worldly Intereſt to ſerve by being of this or that <hi>Party</hi> or <hi>Church.</hi> But if I had, I hope I ſhould prefer the Happineſs of a Life that is <hi>Eternal,</hi> before that of a ſhort and uncertain ſtay here. For this reaſon, 'tis poſſible, I may want one great and moving Argument, which at this <hi>Juncture</hi> eſpecially, many have; for 'tis not this <hi>World's</hi> Riches or Honours that I look after: ſo that if I were even at <hi>Rome</hi> itſelf, the great and ſplendid Allurements there, would not operate upon me. No, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> 'tis pure <hi>Truth and Holineſs</hi> which I am in ſearch of; for I am ſtrongly perſwaded, that without the poſſeſſion of theſe, it is a moſt unreaſonable confidence for any Man to hope to ſee <hi>GOD,</hi> who is Truth and Holineſs itſelf; and therefore their Contraries muſt needs be odious to his <hi>Divine</hi> Majeſty. In a word, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> my whole Deſign here in this World is, firſt to know God's Will, and then to obey and pleaſe him, that through the Merits of my dear <hi>Saviour,</hi> I may be admitted into ſome degree of his Glories hereafter. Now if you can remove my <hi>Doubts,</hi> and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie me by a juſt Anſwer to every <hi>Enquiry,</hi> in this my <hi>Letter,</hi> I ſhall rejoyce to remain where I have been born and bred. But if you cannot, I hope I ſhall deſpiſe the hard and unjuſt Thoughts and Cenſures of Men, and ſo far overcome the <hi>Power and Prejudices of Education and Cuſtom,</hi> as to ſearch for, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <hi>Truth,</hi> in what <hi>Communion</hi> ſoever I find her, in ſpight of all temptations and hinderances. Our <hi>Repreſenter</hi> ſays, <hi>That every
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100283:4"/>Man must work out his own Salvation with fear and trembling:</hi> if ſo, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> you muſt pardon me, if hereafter I take a more particular care of <hi>mine,</hi> even to the forſaking of your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, in caſe I cannot meet with ſatisfaction in it, and by following the clear Commands of Holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> the Dictates of <hi>right</hi> Reaſon, and the aſſiſtances of the <hi>honest and knowing Guides</hi> of another <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I come to the main buſineſs of my <hi>Letter,</hi> give me leave <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> to acquaint you with the ground and occaſion of it; and that was my reading the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation of the <hi>Canons and Decrees of the Council of Trent,</hi> lately by ſome of our Church ſet out here. For indeed till then, and as I had not the perfect uſe of the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, and always living in a blind and ſtupid obedience and reliance upon the honeſty and learning of my Guides, I was ignorant of many neceſſary things, and thought our <hi>Church</hi> never had, nor never could have any thing in her <hi>Doctrines Worſhip and Service,</hi> either <hi>Idolatrous or Superſtitious,</hi> or that any of her Children ever was, or ever could poſſibly be guilty of either; or that any Errors or Abuſes could creep into our Church; and much leſs, that any of her <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> would betray their poor <hi>ignorant Sheep</hi> into thoſe dangers. But now, God be prais'd, I am otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, and that chiefly by reading and conſidering thoſe very <hi>Decrees of Trent,</hi> together with the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> now lately alſo publiſh'd in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> For in many places of thoſe <hi>Decrees,</hi> the <hi>Council</hi> ſhews a great fear (and ſo far cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly 'tis highly to be commended) leaſt the People ſhould run into <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry.</hi> Now, I conſider, that if there was no danger from the <hi>Nature, or from the Uſe and Practice</hi> of our <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> ſuch a concern as the <hi>Council</hi> ſhew'd, had been much below the Wiſdom of ſo great an Aſſembly. So that a thinking Man cannot forbear concluding, that there was very great danger of the Peoples committing <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition,</hi> at leaſt from the very uſe and performing of the <hi>then Worſhip and Service.</hi> However, I would fain hope, that tho' there are ſome things in this <hi>Council,</hi> that look too like <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry;</hi> yet, becauſe we magnifie it for ſo Wiſe and Holy, that it has in Truth Defin'd and Decreed nothing that ſo much as miniſters or tempts to thoſe grievous Sins. For ſince it was in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil's</hi> Power, not only to have actually <hi>redreſs'd all Abuſes</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100283:4"/>Corruptions, but alſo to have prevented all future danger of that kind; and yet if it can be made appear, that it has done nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but rather has ſtill more expos'd Mankind to theſe Sins, I cannot for my life ſee how it can be acquitted of Hypocriſie and Deceit, towards the poor <hi>ignorant</hi> People, which make up, I doubt, the far greateſt part of our <hi>Church:</hi> And that, provided the <hi>Council</hi> might advance the Riches and Grandure of the <hi>Church and Clergy,</hi> it car'd not what became of Mens <hi>Souls,</hi> whom the wiſe and good <hi>GOD</hi> thought worth redeeming, by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Blood of his dear <hi>Son.</hi> Suffer me, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> to give you an inſtance or two, of this <hi>Council's ſeeming Care</hi> to keep Men from <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry;</hi> and which alſo firſt let in ſome light to my dark and ignorant mind.</p>
            <p>
               <q>In the 22 <hi>Seſſion,</hi> and the <hi>Decree concerning the Celebration of the Maſs,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are order'd, to take care to prohibit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thoſe things which <hi>Superſtition</hi> (the falſe Imitatreſs of true Piety) or <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> hath introduced; and ſpeak againſt the <hi>Servitude,</hi> I ſuppoſe, that is, the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>Idols:</hi> And alſo it is there commanded, that a certain number of certain <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Candles,</hi> which was rather invented by a <hi>Superſtitious</hi> Worſhip, than by <hi>true</hi> Religion, ſhould be taken away. And again, in the 25 <hi>Seſſion,</hi> and the <hi>Decree concerning Purgatory,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> are commanded not to ſuffer any thing, but to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit every thing which <hi>tends</hi> to <hi>Superſtition.</hi> And in her <hi>Decree concerning the Invocation of Saints,</hi> &amp;c. ſhe earneſtly deſires that all <hi>Superſtition</hi> in the Invocation of Saints, Worſhipping of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and in the Holy Uſe of Images, may be taken away. And laſt of all, in the Continuation of her 25 <hi>Seſſion,</hi> ſhe ſpeaks againſt <hi>Superſtition and Ignorance.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> finding this <hi>wonderful General Council</hi> to ſpeak ſo plainly againſt theſe Crimes of <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry,</hi> and alſo againſt <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and obſerving it ſo much concern'd for the People, and to give ſuch great caution and charge to the Biſhops about them, and our Adverſaries continually taxing us with theſe Sins, you cannot ſurely blame me, or be the leaſt offended, that I take the beſt way I can deviſe, not only to preſerve my ſelf from them, but alſo others in our Church, who I doubt, may as much want information and help in theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And this indeed is one reaſon, why I chuſe rather to <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire</hi> of you in this <hi>publick</hi> manner, than in a <hi>private</hi> way: for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100283:5"/>I conſider, that that <hi>Love</hi> is not <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> which is confin'd to one's ſelf, its Nature being communicative. And ſince <hi>Charily</hi> to our <hi>Neighbour</hi> is an indiſpenſible Duty, How can it be better exercis'd than about the <hi>Soul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pardon, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> this neceſſary Account of that which gave birth to my <hi>Letter.</hi> And becauſe it will conſiſt of things different in their nature, permit me, for the more clear and orderly proceeding and greater ſatisfaction, to divide it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeveral <hi>Sections,</hi> as well as <hi>Queries.</hi> And take it not ill, that I propoſe to ye the Difficulties I labour under, with that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and openneſs, which only becomes a pure <hi>lover</hi> and <hi>ſearcher</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and one that conſiders nothing but <hi>GOD</hi> and his own <hi>Soul</hi> concern'd in the <hi>Enquiry.</hi> And I humbly beg you to give a <hi>direct, full, and clear</hi> Anſwer to every <hi>Enquiry,</hi> in each <hi>Section;</hi> or a good reaſon why you cannot, or will not.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> I. WHat might be the reaſon, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> why the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> did not define and deſcribe <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition,</hi> eſpecially when it ſo often mentions theſe Crimes, and cautions People againſt them; does not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding make a thinking Man apt to believe, that they were conſcious, that the then <hi>Practice, and Worſhip, and Doctrines,</hi> were faulty in that kind, and ſo were afraid of having them diſcover'd by ſuch an honeſt dealing; but yet were willing to appear to condemn them in <hi>general</hi> terms; for even at that time, was it not too groſs to have declar'd for down-right Idolatry, or Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> II. What might thoſe things be, which the Council in the 22 Seſſion orders <hi>Biſhops</hi> to take care <hi>to prohibit and remove,</hi> and which it obſerv'd, <hi>were introduc'd by Superſtition and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs?</hi> But had it not lookt more honeſt, and more becoming Chriſtian Biſhops, to have told what theſe things were?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> III. What was that <hi>Servitude</hi> or Worſhip of <hi>Idols</hi> it ſpeaks againſt in the ſame Seſſion, in the <hi>Decree concerning the Things to be obſerv'd and eſchew'd in the Celebration of the Maſs?</hi> Did the Prieſt or the People Worſhip <hi>Idols</hi> when Maſs was ſaid? Pray <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> declare the truth to me in this matter,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100283:5"/>my mind is much perplex'd about it. For I find our preſent <hi>Diſputers</hi> ſtifly maintain, that our Doctrine and Worſhip is now the very ſame that it was at the time of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and at that time the ſame it was from the beginning: I profeſs I tremble as often as I go to Maſs, and ſhall do ſo till I am bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſatisfied herein?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IV. What was that certain Number of <hi>Maſſes and Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles,</hi> which in the ſame <hi>Decree</hi> the <hi>Council</hi> ſays was rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by a <hi>Superſtitious Worſhip, than by true Religion?</hi> Are they according to the Council's Command taken away? And when, and where were they ſo taken away?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> V. What does the <hi>Council</hi> mean in her <hi>Decree concerning Purgatory,</hi> by commanding the <hi>Biſhops not to ſuffer any thing, but to prohibit every thing which tends to Superſtition.</hi> Pray <hi>Reverend Fathers</hi> what was it, which at that time did tend to <hi>Superſtition</hi> in the Peoples Practice and Worſhip, in <hi>Praying for the Dead,</hi> or the Souls in <hi>Purgatory?</hi> and is it taken away? and have we no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing yet remaining and in uſe among us, and in our preſent Practice, that is either <hi>Superſtitious</hi> or tends to it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VI. What was that <hi>Superſtition in the Invocation of Saints, Worſhipping of Relicks, and in the Holy Uſe of Images,</hi> which the Council in <hi>Seſſion</hi> 25, ſo earneſtly deſir'd might be taken away? And is that Superſtition taken away? Can none of our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion be guilty of this Sin now? Is there now no danger for us in theſe matters? What aſſurance can you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> give us?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VII. But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> If there was no danger from the very Nature of the Service and Worſhip then in uſe in our Churches, why did that <hi>wiſe Council,</hi> ſhew ſuch a needleſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern and fear. But if there was danger, and the <hi>Council</hi> ſays there was, why did it not declare plainly and openly, wherein particularly the danger lay? Doubtleſs the Council knew it, and ſince it has not told us particularly wherein, and in what manner the danger of <hi>Superſtition</hi> lay, How is it poſſible for any Man to acquit the <hi>Council</hi> from <hi>Hypocriſie and Deceit</hi> towards poor ignorant Souls, which it pretended, and was certainly bound to take care of? How does this <hi>Council's</hi> care of <hi>Souls</hi> appear, ſince the People are now as much in the dark about the nature of <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and wherein the danger lies in <hi>the Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, and Worſhipping Relicks and Images, and Prayers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100283:6"/>for the Dead,</hi> as before the Council met; becauſe it only cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions them in general againſt ſuch Sins, but never particularly tells them how they ſhould know, or avoid them, which yet methinks had been the honeſter courſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VIII. Again, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſeems very ſenſible that the People in the then <hi>current</hi> Worſhip and Service of the Church, were guilty of <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition,</hi> and reprov'd them for it, and commanded a Reformation. Now <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I humbly enquire, Is our Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice the ſame now, as it was at the time of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> if it is, then pray, where is our obedience to that <hi>Council,</hi> and our care of <hi>Souls?</hi> Are not we now as <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious</hi> as the People were then? Why then is not our Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice reform'd? Why are we let alone in an <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Worſhip?</hi> But if our Service and Worſhip be altered and purg'd from thoſe groſs Crimes which were in it at the time of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> then I deſire to know of you, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers,</hi> Whether the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> may not fairly conclude theſe following things againſt us: 1. That our Service and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, even by the confeſſion of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> was then <hi>Idolatrous and Superſtitious.</hi> 2. That this confeſſion juſtifies, at leaſt, the firſt <hi>Reformers,</hi> and alſo the preſent Profeſſors of the <hi>Reform'd</hi> Churches, (unleſs we can make appear that our Service and Worſhip is now free from Superſtition and Idolatry) in their Charge againſt our Church, and their leaving our Communion. 3. That our <hi>Church</hi> is not now the ſame in her Service, and Worſhip, and Doctrines, as ſhe was at the time of the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and then pray <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> where are all our Boaſts of the <hi>Inerrability</hi> of our Church, and the Infallibility of <hi>Tradition,</hi> and ever continuing the ſame in her Doctrines and Worſhip from Father to Son, ſince our Saviour's and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time? Is not this a terrible inſtance to our Adverſaries of our Innovations and Corruptions? And beyond all Reply, does it not juſtifie all their Complaints and Outcries againſt us for theſe things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IX. In the ſame <hi>Decree concerning the Celebration of the Maſs,</hi> the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> complains to this effect, That there were ſeveral Innovations, Errors, and Corruptions <hi>crept in by the Vice of Times, or careleſneſs and diſhoneſty of Men about the Sacrifice of the Maſs.</hi> Now I humbly deſire to know of you, <hi>Reverend
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100283:6"/>Fathers,</hi> the preciſe Time <hi>when,</hi> and the very Perſons by <hi>whom</hi> theſe Abuſes and Corruptions crept into the Maſs? The famous Patrons of <hi>Oral Tradition,</hi> and the Maintainers of <hi>a perpetual, and no ways erring Church,</hi> aſſert, That it is abſolutely impoſſible for any Errors and Corruptions ever to creep into our Doctrine and Worſhip. But I am rather inclin'd to believe the <hi>Council of Trent,</hi> who owns that the <hi>very Sacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> which I think we look upon as the greateſt Myſtery, and of the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in all our Religion, was then horribly corrupted. But <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Fathers,</hi> if you cannot inform me of the preciſe Times <hi>when,</hi> and the Perſons by <hi>whom</hi> the <hi>Holy Sacrifice of the Maſs</hi> was ſo abus'd, as I have ſome reaſon to fear you cannot, in that caſe, I deſire to know, Why we ſhould require that of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> for the Errors and Corruptions, which they ſay are crept into our Doctrines and Practice, which yet we out ſelves can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhew for thoſe Errors and Abuſes which nevertheleſs we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to have come in? And why <hi>the Vice of Times, or the careleſneſs and diſhoneſty of Men,</hi> may not be allow'd of, for a good general account, how Abuſes and Corruptions might creep into <hi>Religion,</hi> from the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as well as from the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> I humbly deſire to know of you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> X. Whether the generality of Mankind is not naturally inclin'd to <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry?</hi> And whether from theſe paſſages of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> which I have quoted, it does not appear, that the bent and inclination of the People of our Communion, was at <hi>that</hi> time extreamly towards <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry?</hi> And whether the Fathers of that <hi>Council</hi> have well and honeſtly taken care to ſecure the People from falling into theſe Sins by their <hi>Decrees and Canons,</hi> about Worſhipping the <hi>Host, Angels, and Saints, with their Images and Relicks?</hi> And whether in human probability the not enjoyning theſe things, but direct prohibiting of them, had not been a more likely and a more honeſt way, not only to draw the People off from their then preſent <hi>Superſtitious and Idolatrous</hi> Inclinations and Practice, but alſo to preſerve them from all future danger and guilt of <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry?</hi> And whether there could have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by the ſubtilty of the <hi>Devil,</hi> any thing (except returning to down-right <hi>Paganiſm</hi>) more effectually to draw and betray Mankind into theſe Sins of <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry;</hi> and if there could, I deſire you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> for mine and others ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to name it?</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100283:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XI. Has the <hi>Church of England</hi> any thing in her <hi>Doctrines or Practice,</hi> in her <hi>Liturgy or Worſhip,</hi> which is either <hi>Superſtitious or Idolatrous,</hi> or any way really ſinful, or that does but tend to lead her Members into them. And if ſhe has not, as I am apt to believe ſhe has not, becauſe I have never heard that any of our Prieſts or Writers of Controverſie ever charg'd that upon her, then pray <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> tell me freely, Whether upon this very account (which ought to be well conſider'd by every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that believes he has a Soul to be ſaved) ſhe has not a vaſt advantage of <hi>our Church;</hi> ſince 'tis ſo manifeſt, that even the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> were ſenſible and confeſt, that there were then <hi>Superſtitious and Idolatrous</hi> Practices in our Church, and that the Members of it might very eaſily, and without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary care of the <hi>Biſhops and Paſtors,</hi> fall into <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XII. Pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What <hi>Original</hi> Treatiſe, Book of Directions, or Sermon, is there ſet out by our Church to preſerve our People from <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition?</hi> Some ſuch thing ſeems to me to be extream neceſſary after what the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> have ſaid of the danger of the Peoples falling into theſe Sins, by their uſe of our <hi>Service and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi> Unleſs you can give ſome good reaſon, why the People of our Communion in <hi>this Age,</hi> are wiſer then in the Age of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XIII. But to conclude this Section, I humbly enquire of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What is the true Definition of <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition?</hi> Pray give me ſuch an one of each diſtinctly and ſeverally, as you'll abide by, and anſwer to our Learned Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, and be content that all our <hi>Doctrines and Worſhip and Practice</hi> ſhall be try'd by. Alſo ſuch an one as is exactly agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Holy Scriptures and Definitions of the Fathers and Doctors of the <hi>Ancient Church.</hi> For I conſider, that the nature of <hi>Idolatry and Superſtition</hi> is the ſame now as it was then. Be pleas'd likewiſe, to let your Definition be ſo full, clear, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as may infallibly (which ſure I may requeſt from the Prieſts of an Infallible Church) guide and direct me, in my <hi>Thoughts, Worſhip, and Adoration of the Holy Sacrament, or Host, and of the Angels and Saints, and of the Croſs and Relicks,</hi> that ſo I may be ſafe from all danger of committing or falling into theſe grievous Sins, or any degree of them. For I infinitely deſire to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100283:7"/>have a right Notion of GOD and his Worſhip, and would not offend and affront him, while I think I am pleaſing and doing him honour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> I. THE Catechiſm of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> now late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Publiſh'd in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> p. 344, ſays, That there is <hi>an Honour which is due to GOD alone, and is not to be given to an Angel:</hi> and <hi>p.</hi> 464, there is a great Charge given, That <hi>what is proper to GOD, be not given to any beſides him.</hi> Now to me it ſeems not a little ſtrange, that in ſo weighty a matter, and wherein both <hi>GOD</hi> and Mankind is ſo much concern'd, that neither the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> nor this <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> when they had ſo fair occaſions, ſhould not I ſay, freely and plainly tell what that <hi>Honour</hi> and Worſhip is, which is <hi>proper and due to GOD a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> and wherein it conſiſts, and by what it is ſignified and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd. This omiſſion is apt to create no very honourable thoughts either of the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> or <hi>Council:</hi> but ſince neither the Fathers of the <hi>Council,</hi> nor the Compoſers of the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> thought convenient to do ſo juſt and honeſt a piece of Service to the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, ſuffer me here, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to enquire of you, What is <hi>that Honour and Worſhip which is proper and due to God only?</hi> Wherein does it conſiſt? And by what Words and Acts is it ſignified and expreſs'd?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> II. How, and in what, does that <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> which by our <hi>Church</hi> we are commanded, and which we do give to the <hi>Angels and Saints,</hi> and particularly to the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> differ from that Worſhip which is <hi>proper to GOD</hi> alone?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> III. How, and in what, does that <hi>Honour, Worſhip, or Veneration,</hi> which we give to <hi>Angels and Saints,</hi> and particularly to the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> differ from that <hi>Honour, Reſpect, or Reverence</hi> we pay to <hi>Kings and Princes, and good Men</hi> upon Earth? By what Words, Acts, or Signs do you diſtinguiſh <hi>this</hi> from <hi>that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IV. Whether the ground and reaſon of our <hi>Worſhip of GOD,</hi> he not his Divine, his Infinite, and Incommunicable Attributes and Perfections, ſuch as his Omnipotence, his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, and Omnipreſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> V. Whether <hi>Prayer, or Religious Invocation,</hi> has not been
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100283:8"/>always lookt on as, and is not, an <hi>eſſential</hi> part of that <hi>Worſhip which is due to GOD alone?</hi> Inſomuch, that <hi>Prayer</hi> is uſually put for the <hi>whole;</hi> and the publick Place of <hi>GOD</hi>'s Worſhip from hence, is by <hi>GOD</hi> himſelf in <hi>Scripture,</hi> call'd, <hi>The Houſe of Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VI. If <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> is due only to <hi>GOD,</hi> and that upon the account <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his <hi>Infinite and Incommunicable Perfections,</hi> are not all <hi>Kinds</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> alſo of <hi>Religious Worſhip,</hi> for the ſame reaſon, peculiar and due to <hi>GOD alone;</hi> unleſs there be ſome other <hi>Being</hi> beſides <hi>GOD,</hi> who has thoſe Infinite Attributes and Perfections? But if all <hi>Kinds</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> of Religious Worſhip be not due to <hi>GOD alone,</hi> I conſider that our <hi>Saviour's</hi> Anſwer to the <hi>Devil,</hi> in the 4 <hi>Chapter,</hi> and 10 <hi>Verſe</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> had been very imperfect. For when the <hi>Devil</hi> would have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored by him, to what purpoſe was that Anſwer of the <hi>Holy Jeſus, It is written, the Lord thy God ſhalt thou adore, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve:</hi> unleſs our <hi>B. Saviour</hi> had intended by it, and by uſing of thoſe two words, <hi>adore and ſerve,</hi> (which I am told in the Original <hi>Greek,</hi> ſignifie and comprehend the meaneſt and loweſt, as well as the higheſt kind and degree of Honour and Service) to include and appropriate all manner, parts, and degrees of <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> to GOD? For who can imagine but that the <hi>Devil</hi> would have been content and very glad if our Saviour would but have worſhipp'd him in any kind, and with the moſt <hi>inferiour</hi> degree of Worſhip?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VII. But beſides, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I farther enquire of you, that if our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> had not by this Anſwer of his to the <hi>Devil,</hi> alſo intended to exclude all the Worſhip of <hi>good</hi> as well as <hi>bad</hi> Spirits, whether 'tis not rational to think he would have anſwer'd the <hi>Devil</hi> thus, <hi>The Lord thy God, and good Spirits ſhalt thou adore, and them only ſhalt thou ſerve?</hi> And whether our Saviour's not mentioning of <hi>good</hi> Spirits, either <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Saints,</hi> or the <hi>B. Virgin,</hi> but on the contrary confining <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> and Service to GOD <hi>Only,</hi> is not an unanſwerable Objection and Argument againſt our Worſhipping of <hi>Saints and Angels toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with GOD,</hi> and ſo makes us guilty of <hi>Idolatry?</hi> For till you oblige me with a perfect <hi>Definition of Idolatry,</hi> and convince me of an Error, at preſent, I humbly conceive <hi>Idolatry</hi> does not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt meerly in forſaking the Worſhip of the <hi>Supreme GOD,</hi> but alſo in Worſhipping any <hi>Being</hi> or thing elſe, together with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100283:8"/>Supreme <hi>GOD,</hi> or while we continue to Worſhip the Supreme <hi>GOD.</hi> But if what I have now diſcours'd from this Anſwer of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> be not the true meaning, I beg you then, to give me the true ſence of it, and prove your Interpretation by <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi>'s Rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VIII. If you ſay, as I hope for the Honour of <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Love of <hi>Truth</hi> you will, that all kinds, parts, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of <hi>Religious Worſhip</hi> are due <hi>only to GOD,</hi> and that <hi>Prayer or Religious Invocation</hi> is a <hi>part</hi> of that <hi>Worſhip;</hi> then <hi>Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> I enquire of you, Whether 'tis not too plain that we <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> in our Religious <hi>Invocation</hi> of, and <hi>Praying to the Saints and Angels,</hi> are highly guilty of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſince the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Saint</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> or even the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> herſelf, is but a <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and we give part of that Honour to it, which is due to <hi>GOD</hi> who created that Angel or Saint? And do not we like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in <hi>Inovocating and Praying</hi> to the <hi>Saints and Angels,</hi> attribute to them at leaſt, <hi>Omniſcience or Omnipreſence,</hi> or elſe what <hi>ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Nonſence is it to pray to them at all? What ſhall we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>GOD,</hi> for thus robbing him of thoſe <hi>Perfections peculiar to his infinite Eſſence?</hi> And what will it avail us at the <hi>Great Day,</hi> to ſay, <hi>Lord we gave but an inferior degree of Religious Worſhip to ſome of thy Creatures which we believ'd more excellent than others, and thy dear Friends:</hi> when at the ſame time the <hi>Angry and Jealous GOD</hi> ſhall tell us, That he had plainly reveal'd to us, <hi>that every part and degree of Religious Worſhip was due only to him, and that Prayer was a principal part of that Worſhip that was peculiar to him?</hi> I ſay, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> what will become of us, when we ſhall be charg'd with giving part of that Honour and Worſhip, tho' never ſo <hi>inferiour,</hi> and for <hi>GOD</hi>'s <hi>ſake too,</hi> to the <hi>Creatures,</hi> which was only due to <hi>GOD</hi> the <hi>Creator?</hi> This is a matter of vaſt conſequence, and therefore I humbly and earneſtly beg you to give me a full Anſwer, for my Mind and Conſcience is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly perplex'd about it. I have a great reſpect for the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> but I muſt needs tell you <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> that I begin to have a far greater regard to the <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IX. But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I muſt trouble you with more Enquiries into this Affair, for I look upon't to be of far greater concern than the generality of our People do. To deal freely with you, till I am much better ſatisfied about the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100283:9"/>of it, I ſhall forbear offering up any <hi>Prayers</hi> either <hi>Vocal</hi> or <hi>Mental,</hi> to the greateſt and moſt glorious <hi>Saint or Angel</hi> in Heaven, or even to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> herſelf: for doubtleſs, as ſlight as we make of the matter, yet a <hi>right Object of Worſhip</hi> is of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite concern, and I am now fully convinc'd, not only, that this Article of <hi>Invocation,</hi> &amp;c. is one of the moſt eſſential in <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> but alſo that no leſs then our Eternal <hi>Salvation</hi> or <hi>Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> depends on't; and therefore let no man think ſtrange that I ſhould ceaſe <hi>Invocating Saints,</hi> till I meet with ample ſatisfaction to my Doubts and Scruples. For I have learnt of St. <hi>Paul, That all that is not of faith is ſin.</hi> And of another <hi>Spiritual Guide, That when a man's mind is in doubt, the ſafer part is to be choſen:</hi> and in Religious Doubts, <hi>that which is moſt for the Honour of GOD;</hi> which at preſent, I am perſwaded, <hi>praying</hi> to, and depending upon him <hi>alone</hi> is. But I enquire, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Whether any <hi>Creature</hi> tho' never ſo excellent, whether it be <hi>Angel</hi> or <hi>Saint,</hi> or even the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> herſelf, has any <hi>natural</hi> and inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Right, to any <hi>kind</hi> or <hi>degree</hi> of <hi>Religious Worſhip?</hi> If it has, I deſire you to make it out; if it has not, then I <hi>enquire,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to juſtifie a Practice of ſuch vaſt moment, we are not bound to ſhew an expreſs poſitive Law of <hi>GOD?</hi> And if there be ſuch an expreſs <hi>Divine</hi> Command, I beſeech you <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> for mine, and the quiet of other mens Conſciences in this weighty matter, to produce it. But if you can neither ſhew that the moſt excellent <hi>Creature</hi> imaginable, has a <hi>natural Right,</hi> nor an <hi>expreſs Command from GOD,</hi> for any kind or part of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi> Worſhip, then I further ask, How can our Church in <hi>commanding,</hi> and we in <hi>giving Religious</hi> Worſhip to Saints and Angels, be acquitted from groſs <hi>Idolatry?</hi> And how can the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> be guilty of the leaſt Sin, for refuſing, and not doing an Action for which there is neither a Law of <hi>GOD</hi> or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> But I further enquire <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> and ſuppoſing the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are miſtaken, and are over nice and curious in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to give any <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> to <hi>Angels and excellent Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Whether they are not in a much more innocent and pardonable condition, than we of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſince they do not give that <hi>Religious</hi> Worſhip to the <hi>Angels and Saints,</hi> which inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently they might have done, but were not bound to it by any Law of <hi>GOD,</hi> and refus'd to do it, not out of any contempt or diſreſpect to thoſe <hi>excellent Spirits,</hi> but purely through a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100283:9"/>mighty reverence to <hi>GOD,</hi> and fear of giving his <hi>incommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Glory to a <hi>Creature?</hi> But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I have a mighty dread upon me, that at the Great Day we ſhall have nothing to plead for our ſelves, in caſe we be miſtaken, in giving any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>Religious</hi> Worſhip, tho' never ſo <hi>ſmall,</hi> to <hi>Creatures,</hi> which is <hi>all</hi> due only to the <hi>Supreme GOD?</hi> For tell me ſincerely, what can we offer in our excuſe? No <hi>poſitive Law of GOD,</hi> for that, I doubt, forbids all <hi>Creature-Worſhip;</hi> nor the Principles of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon, for a very ſmall meaſure of <hi>Natural Light,</hi> tells us, we cannot, and we ought not, <hi>Religiouſly</hi> to Worſhip any other <hi>Being,</hi> than that which guides us, and preſerves our <hi>Being?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> X. Though I have already, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> in this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, made ſome Enquiries concerning the Nature of that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which is due to <hi>GOD only,</hi> and that which is due to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Creatures;</hi> yet I cannot forbear enquiring further, upon my meeting ſince with what the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſays, in <hi>p.</hi> 344, concerning <hi>the Worſhip and Invocation</hi> of Saints, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <q>That whereas we read that the Angels refus'd to be worſhipp'd by Men; it muſt be underſtood that they did ſo, becauſe they would not have that <hi>Honour</hi> done to them, which was due to <hi>GOD alone.</hi> For the Holy Spirit, who ſays Honour and Glory be to <hi>GOD Only,</hi> the ſame has commanded to honour our <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Elders.</hi> Beſides Holy Men who Worſhipped one <hi>GOD only,</hi> did adore Kings alſo, <hi>i. e.</hi> did humbly reverence them.</q> Now here, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> give me leave humbly to enquire of you, Whether that <hi>Honour</hi> which is due to <hi>GOD alone,</hi> and this Honour which we are commanded to give to our <hi>Parents and Elders, and to Kings,</hi> is of the ſame kind and nature, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer only in <hi>Degrees?</hi> If it differs only in degrees, how many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees are due to GOD <hi>alone,</hi> and how many to his excellent <hi>Creatures,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Angels and Saints,</hi> and where is this determin'd in Scripture, for that I muſt tell you, I take to be the only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Revelation of the Will of GOD? Or is the one of a quite different nature and kind from the other? And if they be, then pray, By what Names do ye diſtinguiſh them? By what Acts and Signs are they expreſs'd and known? I have yet heard but of two ſorts or kinds of <hi>Worſhip and Honour,</hi> &amp;c. either <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Divine,</hi> or <hi>Civil.</hi> Now <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I take <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Civil Honour,</hi> to be as different in their natures and kinds, as GOD and Men are; therefore I humbly enquire of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100283:10"/>You, Which of theſe two ſorts of Honour, does this <hi>Trent-Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm</hi> ſay, The <hi>Angels</hi> refus'd, as not <hi>theirs,</hi> but <hi>GOD's due only?</hi> And what <hi>Honour</hi> was it that the <hi>Angels</hi> were willing to have receiv'd, was it <hi>Religious</hi> or <hi>Civil?</hi> And whatever Honour it was, can you prove from <hi>Scripture,</hi> that the ſame kind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Honour is due to the <hi>Saints</hi> alſo? And is the ſame Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, both kinds and degrees, which is due to <hi>Angels and Saints,</hi> alſo due to our <hi>Parents, and Elders, and to Kings?</hi> This <hi>Catechiſm</hi> in my opinion ſeems to ſay ſo. But to deal freely, the darkneſs and confuſion I obſerve in this Book, about ſo important a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, does not look well, I appeal to you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it had not really been more fair and honeſt, intelligible, and inſtructive, when the Authors of this <hi>Catechiſm</hi> were treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of honouring <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>Angels,</hi> &amp;c. plainly to have told us, what kind and degree of Honour was proper and due to <hi>GOD,</hi> what to the <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> and what to our <hi>Parents, Elders,</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> and by what Words and Acts ſuch Honour is to be expreſs'd? But ſince they have not, I humbly beg it of you, and till I receive your Information, I ſhall conclude, that we are only to pay ſuch an Honour to <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> as we do to our <hi>Parents,</hi> &amp;c. which I think we call <hi>Civil,</hi> and not <hi>Religious</hi> Honour, which I think conſiſts in Love, Reſpect, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But was it ever heard that any body here in <hi>England,</hi> for example, and in their Senſes, ever put up <hi>formal and ſolemn Prayer,</hi> either <hi>Vocal</hi> or <hi>Mental,</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> or in their <hi>Cloſets,</hi> to their <hi>Parents, &amp;c.</hi> which might be in <hi>China,</hi> or <hi>Virginia,</hi> or but in <hi>France.</hi> I ſhall therefore, henceforward, pay a great degree of Love and Reſpect for the <hi>B. Angels and Saints,</hi> but I ſhall forbear <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> to <hi>Invoke,</hi> or <hi>Pray</hi> to them: 1. Becauſe they are but my <hi>Fellow-Creatures.</hi> And, 2. Becauſe 'tis much more abſurd and unreaſonable to call upon them, then to call upon my <hi>Parents</hi> in a far Country, becauſe their diſtance from me is ſuppos'd to be incomparably greater, and that I have no more aſſurance that they hear me, than I have that my <hi>Parents</hi> hear me, and ſo my Prayers are equally vain and impertinent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XI. But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Does not that place of the Prophet <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 65. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>O thou that hearest prayer, unto thee ſhall all fleſh come:</hi> and that other Text in the 10 Chapter of <hi>Rom.</hi> v. 14. <hi>How then ſhall they invocate, in whom they have not believ'd:</hi> very plainly prove theſe things: 1. That none but
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100283:10"/>GOD can hear our Prayers. And, 2. For that very reaſon all Mankind is directed to offer up their Prayers to him alone. 3. That we cannot, nor ought not to invocate, or pray to any <hi>Being,</hi> but what we <hi>Believe in?</hi> And do we uſe to ſay, that we <hi>Believe in</hi> any but <hi>in GOD?</hi> In the <hi>Creed,</hi> we ſay, I believe <hi>in</hi> GOD, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But who ſays, that knows what he ſays, <hi>I Believe in the Arch Angel St.</hi> Michael, or <hi>I Believe in St.</hi> Peter, or <hi>I Believe in the Virgin</hi> Mary? If then we do not Believe in, <hi>i. e.</hi> put our hope, truſt, and confidence in the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> or any other <hi>Saints</hi> which are but <hi>Creatures,</hi> as we do <hi>Believe in GOD the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> why ſhould we invocate and pray unto them? What Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as well as Folly is this? But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> if this be not the true meaning of theſe two Texts, I humbly enquire of you, what is the <hi>Infallible</hi> Sence of them, and how I may be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly</hi> certain that what you ſay is the Sence, is indeed ſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XII. But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I am not ignorant that ſome of our Church argue that we ought to pray <hi>to</hi> Saints and Angels, becauſe they pray <hi>for</hi> us. Now not to diſpute with you about this conſequence, let me only humbly ask you, Whether the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, either in their publick or private Worſhip pray'd to the <hi>Angels?</hi> Surely the Angels were in Heaven before as well as ſince the coming of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and pray'd for Mankind too, and yet if you cannot prove that the <hi>Jews</hi> pray'd to, and invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated them, as we now do them, and the Bleſſed Saints; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, how does it follow, that becauſe Angels and Saints pray <hi>for</hi> us men, that therefore we are to pray <hi>to</hi> them? But in good earneſt, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Is not the true queſtion in this matter, not whether thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Spirits</hi> pray <hi>for us,</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are to pray <hi>to them?</hi> Now we ſay, that they are to be pray'd unto, but can we prove it, either from any Principles of <hi>Natural</hi> Reaſon, or any <hi>poſitive</hi> Divine Law of <hi>GOD?</hi> The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſay, they are not to be pray'd <hi>unto,</hi> and think they ſufficiently prove what they ſay, when they produce not only an <hi>expreſs</hi> Law of <hi>GOD</hi> deliver'd by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> which forbids any other <hi>Being</hi> to be Worſhipp'd but the <hi>Supreme GOD;</hi> but alſo our <hi>Saviour's</hi> Anſwer to the <hi>Devil, That GOD only is to be adored, or worſhipp'd, and ſerv'd:</hi> as alſo from other places of Holy Scripture, that <hi>Prayer</hi> is an eſſential part of that Worſhip which is <hi>peculiar to GOD.</hi> So that, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not prove ſome of theſe things following, have not the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100283:11"/>infinitly the better of us in this weighty matter? either, 1. That GOD gave no ſuch Law to the <hi>Jews:</hi> or, 2. That he has Repeal'd it: or, 3. That our <hi>Saviour</hi> when he told the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that GOD <hi>only was to be Worſhipp'd;</hi> yet he meant that <hi>Good</hi> Spirits, but not <hi>Evil,</hi> were likewiſe to be Worſhipp'd <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with GOD?</hi> So that I humbly ask, What ſignifies to any rational Man, that Argument of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> viz. <hi>That it is good and profitable humbly to pray to the Saints,</hi> unleſs we can ſhew plainly that GOD has commanded it? Is the Authority of a <hi>Council,</hi> tho' never ſo <hi>General,</hi> ſufficient to repeal an <hi>expreſs</hi> Law of <hi>GOD,</hi> which ſays, <hi>GOD only is to be Worſhipp'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XIII. Beſides, <hi>Reverend. Fathers,</hi> I obſerve, that when the Authors of the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> p. 464. go about to prove <hi>who is to be pray'd to,</hi> and that GOD is to be pray'd to, they do it not only by <hi>Scripture,</hi> viz. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.15. <hi>Call upon me in the day of tribulation,</hi> but affirm, That <hi>the very Light of Nature implanted in the Souls of Men, teaches it.</hi> But in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry next Section, when they come to treat of <hi>Praying to Saints,</hi> they only ſay, <hi>We fly to the Aſſiſtance of the Saints that are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to whom alſo that Prayers are to be made, has been held ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in the Church of GOD, that to pious Men there can ariſe no doubt.</hi> Now <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I humbly enquire of you, that if either in this place, or in the 344 <hi>p.</hi> where they alſo treated of this matter, they could have produced any direct proofs, either from <hi>Scripture</hi> or the <hi>Light of Nature,</hi> is it imaginable that they would have omitted them here, and have contented themſelves with only ſaying, <hi>That Prayers to Saints has been held ſo certain in the Church of GOD, that to pious Men there can be no doubt?</hi> And whether this <hi>ample</hi> proof of theirs for <hi>Prayer to GOD,</hi> and their <hi>no</hi> proof for <hi>Prayer to Saints,</hi> is not a <hi>loud</hi> confeſſion of our <hi>Church,</hi> that we cannot prove <hi>Invocation of Saints</hi> lawful: eſpecially too, when a Man conſiders, that the very beſt proof and argument the <hi>great Council of Trent</hi> was able to produce was only this, <hi>That it is good and profitable:</hi> but not a word that it is either command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>GOD,</hi> or dictated to us by the <hi>Light of Nature.</hi> Will not any man that believes it to be of vaſt moment, to have a right <hi>Object</hi> of Worſhip, conſider theſe things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XIV. When our <hi>B. Lord</hi> ſet us a pattern how to Pray, he directs us only to ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. and to preſent our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to <hi>GOD alone.</hi> Now if <hi>Christ</hi> would have had us pray
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100283:11"/>to <hi>Saints and Angels</hi> alſo, I humbly enquire of you, <hi>Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> Whether ſo mean a thought can enter into any ſober Man's Head, as to think, that our <hi>B. Saviour</hi> would have conceal'd, or omitted <hi>That,</hi> or any thing elſe, in ſo important a matter as <hi>Prayer,</hi> which either had been our <hi>Duty,</hi> or had been but <hi>good and profitable</hi> to us in our way to Heaven? And whether our Lord's not having done this, <hi>i. e.</hi> not advis'd us to <hi>pray to Saints and Angels,</hi> as well as to <hi>GOD,</hi> is not a good <hi>negative</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt our <hi>Practice?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XV. Farther I enquire of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>GOD</hi> intended by the coming of <hi>Christ</hi> to root <hi>Idolatry</hi> out of the World? If he did, as I hope you'll ſay he did, Whether 'tis poſſible for a <hi>rational</hi> Man to think, that as one <hi>effectual means</hi> to that <hi>end,</hi> our Saviour ever deſign'd to ſet up the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Worſhip of Saints and Angels, and praying before Images and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures?</hi> Can, I ſay, a rational man be of ſo <hi>extravagant Faith,</hi> as to believe that the Bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> who came to deſtroy all <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Worſhip,</hi> then ſo much practis'd in the <hi>Heathen</hi> World, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſet up a new kind of <hi>Creature and Image-Worſhip,</hi> only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Mens Notions and Opinions about it, and changing their <hi>Country Gods</hi> into <hi>Heavenly Saints and Angels, and the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,</hi> and giving new Names to their <hi>Statues and Images?</hi> If a man, I ſay, can once bring himſelf to believe that our Saviour intended by this <hi>means</hi> to cure mens inclinations towards <hi>Idolatry,</hi> I deſire to know of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> what can come amiſs to ſuch a Man's Faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XVI. Again, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I read in the 344. <hi>p.</hi> of our <hi>Trent</hi> Catechiſm, that the <hi>Holy Spirit ſays, Honour and Glory be to GOD only.</hi> But pray then, How comes it to paſs, that many of our <hi>Authors of Devotion</hi> (and particularly a late one, that has ſet forth the <hi>Contemplations on the Life and Glory of Holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> &amp;c.) ſay, <hi>Glory be to Jeſus and Mary?</hi> Methinks, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> this joyning the Bleſſed Virgin with the Holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> and Saviour of the World, and giving her <hi>equal Praiſe, Honour, and Glory,</hi> with GOD, at beſt, looks a little diſobedient to the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit,</hi> and is very undecent. But if <hi>Glory,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be due to GOD only,</hi> as you own the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> itſelf ſays, What bold <hi>blaſphemous</hi> Wretches are we then to give it to a <hi>Creature?</hi> And this Author, I obſerve, makes no difference between <hi>Jeſus and Mary,</hi> in his giving <hi>Honour and Glory,</hi> muſt not any one conclude then, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100283:12"/>the ſame Honour and <hi>Glory</hi> is given to <hi>Mary</hi> as to <hi>Jeſus?</hi> The horrour of which makes me tremble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XVII. But further I enquire of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Whether <hi>Religious Praiſe,</hi> as well as <hi>Prayer,</hi> is not an <hi>eſſential</hi> part of the <hi>Worſhip of GOD?</hi> And whether by it we poor <hi>Creatures,</hi> do not pay that <hi>Homage</hi> which is proper and due to the <hi>Divine Majeſty only?</hi> And whether this <hi>Hymn</hi> of <hi>Glory be,</hi> &amp;c. has not from the very firſt Ages, always been us'd as a <hi>peculiar Form</hi> of giving <hi>Praiſe, Honour, and Glory to GOD, and the Holy Trinity?</hi> And if ſo, Whether by our ſaying, <hi>Glory be to Jeſus and Mary,</hi> we do not <hi>equally</hi> Worſhip <hi>Her</hi> with <hi>Jeſus?</hi> Give <hi>equal Glory, and Honour, and Praiſe</hi> to a <hi>Creature,</hi> as to <hi>GOD the Almighty Creator,</hi> and one of the Perſons of the <hi>B. Trinity?</hi> And whether this is not both downright <hi>Sacriledge and Idolatry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XVIII. But <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> upon a Friend of mine, (with whom I often confer about theſe matters, and who is as much diſſatisfied as myſelf) I ſay, upon his Engliſhing to me this <hi>Verſicle,</hi> in the <hi>Office for the Feſtival of St.</hi> Mar. ad Nives, <hi>viz. Make me worthy to praiſe thee, O Holy Virgin;</hi> and alſo out of the ſame <hi>Office,</hi> this <hi>Prayer</hi> or <hi>Leſſon,</hi> which is ſaid upon the <hi>Second Day of the Octave of the Nativity of the B. Virgin,</hi> viz. <q>O <hi>B. Mary,</hi> who can ſufficiently give thee <hi>Praiſe and Thanks,</hi> who by thy ſingular aſſent, didſt ſuccour the World when it was undone? What <hi>Praiſes</hi> ſufficient can frail Mankind pay unto thee, who has found a way of recovery only by thy commerce with <hi>GOD?</hi> We therefore pray thee receive our <hi>Thanksgivings,</hi> how mean ſoever they be, and unequal to thy Merits.</q> I ſay, I yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquire of you, Whether <hi>Religious Praiſe</hi> has not always been counted the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of a Chriſtian? And if <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> which the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux</hi> acknowledges to be a
<note n="*" place="margin">Expoſition, Sect. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>principal part of that interiour Adoration</hi> which is due to GOD, <hi>and cannot be offer'd to any but to him, becauſe by it we make a publick Acknowledgment, and a ſolemn Proteſtation of GOD's Soveraignty, and our abſolute depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance.</hi> How can we, without being guilty of <hi>Blaſphemy and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry,</hi> by <hi>this Prayer,</hi> and that Hymn before mention'd, <hi>viz. Glory be to,</hi> &amp;c. (which by all other Chriſtians at leaſt, except us, was ever us'd as a <hi>peculiar and appropriated Form of Praiſing GOD and the Holy Trinity</hi>) offer up this <hi>Sacrifice of Praiſe,</hi> &amp;c. to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> who is confeſſedly but a <hi>Creature?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:100283:12"/>
               <p>But beſides, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Pray, How comes it to paſs that in this <hi>Prayer</hi> we attribute to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> the <hi>finding out the Recovery</hi> of loſt Mankind? I profeſs, I always thought that we <hi>Chriſtians</hi> at leaſt, made the Holy <hi>Trinity</hi> the ſole <hi>Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> of the <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> of Mankind. Is not ſo mighty a Work a little too big for a <hi>Creature</hi> to deviſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> I. <hi>REverend Fathers,</hi> as I am exceſſively <hi>diſſatisfy'd</hi> in my Conſcience about this <hi>Invocation of the Virgin Mary, and other Saints;</hi> ſo I cannot leave off making larger <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries</hi> into the matter; my next therefore ſhall be, Whether we <hi>Catholicks</hi> do not <hi>exceed</hi> the Bounds and Rules which the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> and other Books ſet out, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by our <hi>Church,</hi> does preſcribe us about <hi>Praying to Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Now I humbly conceive the Truth in this matter will be beſt diſcover'd, Firſt by ſeeing how far <hi>Authority</hi> ſays we <hi>may</hi> go: and Secondly, how far we <hi>do</hi> actually go in this Practice. The <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, p.</hi> 464. ſays, <hi>We do not pray to GOD, and to the Saints af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame manner. To God we pray, either to give us the good things we want, or to deliver us from evil: But to the Saints we pray, (becauſe they are in favour with GOD) to undertake our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, and to beg of GOD thoſe things we want. Hence we have two ways of Praying differing in the manner; for we properly ſay to GOD,</hi> Have mercy upon us, hear us; <hi>but to the Saints,</hi> Pray for us: and it adds, That <hi>we must take heed, that what is proper to GOD, we give not to any beſides him.</hi> And the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> who by <hi>ſome</hi> of us is thought to have given the true <hi>ſence</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> in the <hi>Advertiſement of his Expoſition,</hi> p. 11. ſays, <hi>That we pray to them with the ſame mind we pray to our Brethren, who are upon Earth with us, that is, to pray with us, and for us, to our Common Maſter, in the Name of our Common Mediator, who is Jeſus Christ.</hi> And in his <hi>Expoſition, Sect.</hi> 4. he ſays, That <hi>the Church teaches us to pray to the Saints in the ſame Spirit of Charity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame Order of Fraternal Society, which moves us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand aſſiſtance of our Brethren living upon Earth.</hi> And our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter,</hi> p. 4, 5. ſays, <hi>That as almost every ſick Man deſires the Congregation to be his Mediators,</hi> i. e. <hi>to be remembred in their Prayers, ſo he deſires the Bleſſed in Heaven to be his Mediators, that is, that they would pray to GOD for him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:100283:13"/>
               <p>And is not this, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> and the utmoſt, that by our <hi>Church</hi> we are allow'd to do? Shall we now ſee whether, neither many of our <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Guides</hi> Teach, nor our <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> itſelf <hi>Practice,</hi> a great deal more in their <hi>Devotions</hi> to the <hi>Saints,</hi> and principally to the <hi>B. Virgin?</hi> And will not this be beſt known by our <hi>Publick Offices,</hi> and other <hi>allow'd Books of Devotion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I begin then with the <hi>Offices</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> which I hope will be allow'd of as an Authentick Proof: for if <hi>they</hi> may not be admitted to prove our <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> I know not how it can be done, but by being preſent with every individual Man when he is at his Prayers and Devotion, which I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive is next to impoſſible.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Office</hi> then, of St. <hi>Mar. ad Nives,</hi> in the Second Day of the Octave of her Nativity, my aforeſaid <hi>Friend</hi> Engliſh'd to me this <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> out of the <hi>Leſſon</hi> or <hi>Prayer</hi> to the B. Virgin, <hi>O, admit our Prayers within the Sanctuary of thy Audience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And out of the <hi>Offic. Parv. B. Mariae,</hi> this Prayer of our Church to her, <hi>We fly unto thy Protection and Safe-guard, O Holy Mother of GOD, deſpiſe not our Prayers in our Neceſſities, but always deliver us from all dangers, O Glorious and B. Virgin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe out of the <hi>Office B. M. in Sabbato,</hi> &amp;c. and the <hi>Hymn</hi> which begins <hi>Ave Maris Stella,</hi> this Prayer; <hi>Hail Star of the World,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>Looſe the Bonds of guilty Sinners, enlighten the eyes of the Blind, drive away all Sins from us, make us humble and chaſt, and free from the Bonds of our Sins; give us purity of Life, and grant us a ſafe paſſage into the next World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the aforeſaid <hi>Office, Parv. B. M.</hi> this Prayer, <hi>Protect us from the Enemy, and receive us at the hour of Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe out of the <hi>Brev. Rom.</hi> he Engliſh'd to me this <hi>Leſſon or Prayer</hi> to the <hi>B. Virgin, Accept that we offer, give that we ask, and pardon that we fear, becauſe thou art the</hi> Only <hi>hope of Sinners. We hope for the pardon of our Sins by thee, and in thee is the most bleſſed expectation of our Reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the <hi>proper Maſs of her Seven Sorrows,</hi> and the Solemn <hi>Hymn,</hi> which begins, <hi>Stabat Mater doloroſa,</hi> this other ſtrange Prayer, <hi>Make our Hearts to burn with the Love of Chriſt,—Defend us in the Day of Judgment—And grant that when our Souls depart from our Bodies, they may go into the Glory of Paradice.</hi> By my Friend's help, I could have produced ſeveral other Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100283:13"/>and Expreſſions to the B. V. and other Saints, in as high ſtrains as theſe, but I ſuppoſe theſe may ſuffice for my purpoſe. Let me now, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> ſee what ſome of our <hi>eminent</hi> and allow'd of <hi>Writers</hi> and <hi>Guides</hi> teach our People.</p>
               <p>I begin with Cardinal <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> and who is alſo a <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niz'd Saint.</hi> Out of the Office he has compos'd, call'd <hi>Coroná B. V.</hi> the <hi>Grown</hi> of the B. Virgin, which is found in his Sixth Tome, and the Edition of <hi>Rome,</hi> 1588, my Friend Engliſh'd to me this <hi>Orizon; O Empreſs, and our most kind Lady, by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Mother,</hi> Command <hi>thy most beloved Son, our Lord Jeſus Christ, that he would vouchſafe to lift up our minds,</hi> &amp;c. And in his 35 <hi>Pſalm</hi> of his <hi>Lady's Pſalter,</hi> he hath theſe Words; <hi>Incline the Countenance of GOD upon us,</hi> Compel <hi>him to have Mercy upon us Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next I ſhall produce, is a <hi>Little Book,</hi> which I have by me, and which till of late, that my <hi>Underſtanding</hi> is a little better inform'd, I conſtantly us'd, it is call'd, <hi>The Pſalter of the B. Virgin;</hi> it was Compos'd firſt in <hi>French,</hi> by a Father of your <hi>Society,</hi> and after, in the Year 1624, <hi>Tranſlated</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and Printed with Allowance, the <hi>Tranſlator</hi> aſſures the Lady to whom he Dedicated it, that it was well approv'd of by the better ſort of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and was preſented to one of the greateſt <hi>Queens</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> Tongue. In the <hi>First Petition</hi> there are theſe Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <q>O Glorious Virgin, grant me <hi>Grace,</hi> that I may receive pardon for my Sins.—I have this only Refuge, to caſt myſelf under the Shadow of your Wings.—Give my Soul entrance into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, when it ſhall leave the Body,—And let all that is due unto me for my Sins, be cancell'd by your <hi>Merits</hi>—Let the greatneſs of your <hi>Mercy,</hi> blot out the multitude of mine Offences, ſupplying by your <hi>Merits,</hi> what in Juſtice I dare not <hi>demand.</hi> Turn not your Face away from me, for I put my <hi>Trust</hi> in you. I will humble my heart before you, for I know that the Proud ſhall not be entertain'd near unto your <hi>Sacred Majeſty.</hi>
                  </q> In the <hi>Second Petition</hi> theſe, <q>As ſoon as you extend <hi>your Hand</hi> upon the Sick, they are healed, and the Waves of this troubleſome World are ſoon appeas'd by <hi>your Commandment</hi>—Receive my Soul into your Hands, when it ſhall leave this mortal Body, and take it into your Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for it will be loſt with fear, and will not know to what ſide to turn, to ſave itſelf, unleſs under the ſhadow of <hi>your Mercy.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100283:14"/>And in the <hi>Third Petition,</hi> to omit the reſt, there are theſe Words, <q>O Bleſſed Virgin, <hi>Mother of Unlimited Power,</hi> ador'd and call'd upon by the Univerſe, give me ſtrength to reſiſt the Temptations of my inviſible Enemies,—If you ſhould have forſaken me, to whom ſhould I have then repair'd, that would have lookt upon me with pity and compaſſion?</q>
               </p>
               <p>My Friend alſo Engliſh'd to me, the other-day, out of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Bona's Horolog. Aſcet.</hi> or <hi>Monaſtick Clock,</hi> ſome Expreſſions of the ſame nature. This Cardinal, I am told, either is now alive, or but lately dead, and is an approv'd Writer, as well as of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Place and Dignity in our Church. In this Piece of his, he thus addreſſes himſelf to the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> And who can doubt that he would have all others do ſo too? <q>Protect me, O ſweeteſt Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> under the ſhadow of thy Wings. What can I do without thee, O Bleſſed Virgin, or what would become of me, if thou ſhouldſt turn away thy Face from me? I had rather undergo the Pains of <hi>Hell,</hi> than that thy Glory and Dignity ſhould be the leaſt diminiſh'd for a moment of time. Let all that know thy Name, truſt in thee, O Glorious Virgin, becauſe thou doſt not forſake thoſe that truſt in thee. Let the Light of thy Countenance appear unto me in my Agony; and let thy Comfort (moſt merciful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) make glad my departing Soul.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt <hi>Book</hi> I ſhall make uſe of in this matter, is one I have already in my Sixteenth Enquiry of the Second <hi>Section</hi> mention'd, <hi>viz. Contemplations on the Life and Glory of Holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> &amp;c. By <hi>J. C.</hi> D. D. Licens'd by your Society, and Printed in our own Tongue, in the Year 1685.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Epiſtle Dedicatory,</hi> the Author teaches, That the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>is not only Empreſs of Seraphims,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>The most exact O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of Practical Perfection, which the Omnipotence of GOD ever drew; but that by innumerable Titles, ſhe claims the</hi> Utmoſt <hi>Duty of every Chriſtian, as a proper Homage to her Greatneſs.</hi> And in the Book, <hi>p.</hi> 7. he ſays, That <hi>whatever Gifts are beſtow'd upon us by Jeſus, we receive them by the Mediation of</hi> Mary.—<hi>That 'tis one great Mark of the Predeſtination of the Elect, to be ſingularly Devoted to</hi> Mary.—<hi>Nor hath any one Petition'd</hi> Mary, <hi>who was refus'd by</hi> Jeſus, <hi>or truſted in</hi> Mary, <hi>and was abandon'd by</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. And <hi>p.</hi> 12, 13, 14. <hi>That we must chuſe her to be our Adoptive Mother, Patroneſs, and Advocate, and intrust her with whatever
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100283:14"/>we are, have, do, or hope, in Life, Death, and through all Eternity. That we are in the Preſence of Holy</hi> Mary, <hi>and that ſhe ever ſurveys the preſent ſtate of our Souls, all our Thoughts and Projects, and every tract of our Converſation, and therefore that we must put our ſelves wholly under her Protection.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 22. in the <hi>Reſolution,</hi> he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches us to <hi>reſolve</hi> thus: <hi>I will obſerve thee as my Soveraign Lady, Adoptive Mother, and most powerfull Patroneſs, relying on thy Bowels of Mercy, in all my Wants, Petitions, and Tribulations of Body and Mind.</hi> And then immediately follows <hi>The Praiſe,</hi> as he calls it, in this manner, Hail <hi>Mary,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Verſ. <hi>Open my Lips, O Mother of</hi> Jeſus;</item>
                  <item>Reſp. <hi>And my Soul ſhall ſpeak forth thy Praiſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Verſ. <hi>Divine Lady, be intent to my aid;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Reſp. <hi>Graciouſly make haſt to help me.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Verſ. <hi>Glory be to</hi> Jeſus <hi>and</hi> Mary.</item>
                  <item>Reſp. <hi>As it was, is, and ever ſhall be.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I could, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> have been a great deal larger in my Quotations, not only from theſe <hi>Offices and Books of Devotion,</hi> I have now mention'd, but alſo from divers others, as <hi>Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine de Buſti in Mariali,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Bonaventure</hi>'s Works, to wit, St. <hi>Athanaſius's Creed,</hi> the <hi>Litany,</hi> the <hi>Benedicite,</hi> the <hi>Benedictus,</hi> and the other <hi>Hymns</hi> of <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> all turn'd and apply'd (as I am told) by this <hi>Cardinal,</hi> to the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of the Power and Goodneſs of the <hi>Virgin Mary;</hi> to which I could alſo have added, a preſent <hi>French</hi> Author of your <hi>Society,</hi> one Father <hi>Craſſet,</hi> his <hi>Veritable Devotion envers la Sainte Vierge,</hi> &amp;c. with ſeveral others; but I fear'd this would not only ſwell my <hi>Letter,</hi> beyond its intended bounds, but prove tedious to my <hi>Readers:</hi> let this then, if you pleaſe, ſuffice. And now, <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers,</hi> will you ſuffer me to review this Query from the beginning, and upon the whole matter to ask you ſome ſerious and important Queſtions, which naturally, and neceſſarily offer themſelves?</p>
               <p>And firſt, Whether the <hi>good Things we want,</hi> and <hi>the Evil we would be deliver'd from,</hi> be not the very <hi>Matter</hi> of our <hi>Prayers?</hi> And if they be, Whether it was fairly done of the Authors of the <hi>Trent-Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm,</hi> to call them only the <hi>Manner?</hi> ſince even common Sence tells a Man, that <hi>Good and Evil</hi> are the very <hi>Matter,</hi> the things
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100283:15"/>of our <hi>Prayers,</hi> and not the <hi>manner</hi> of asking them. 2. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Caveat</hi> which they gave, <hi>To take heed that what is proper to GOD, we give not to any beſides him,</hi> is not enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince any conſidering Man, not only that our Practice of <hi>Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the Saints</hi> is extream full of Danger for the ignorant People, but alſo that they very well knew it too? And, 3. Since 'tis apparent, that they were ſenſible, that very eaſily the ignorant People might give <hi>that to the Saints, which was proper to GOD,</hi> Whether they had not acted more like <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Fathers of the <hi>Church,</hi> and Lovers of Souls, if either they had told men plainly, ſo that it had been next to impoſſible to miſtake, what was <hi>due to GOD,</hi> and what to the <hi>Saints?</hi> or elſe abſolutely to have forbidden <hi>Praying</hi> at all to <hi>Saints,</hi> (unleſs they could have made it appear, either by the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> or by ſome <hi>poſitive</hi> Law of <hi>GOD,</hi> that it is a Duty commanded, which in my Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth <hi>Quere</hi> of the Second <hi>Section,</hi> I have ſhew'd they never pretended to) and honeſtly have declar'd to Men, That it was both <hi>wiſeſt and ſafeſt for them,</hi> and moſt for the <hi>Honour of GOD,</hi> to put up their <hi>Prayers</hi> to him only, through the alone Merits, Mediation, and Interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt our dear and only Saviour and Redeemer? 4. Whether in your Conſcience you do believe, and by ſound Arguments can prove, that the <hi>People</hi> who are naturally prone to <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry,</hi> had not been, I will not ſay only abundantly more, but abſolutely ſafe from all danger of falling into thoſe grievous Sins, if only they had been taught, and enjoin'd, to offer up their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Praiſes to GOD alone,</hi> through Jeſus Chriſt? And whether through the contrary <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of Praying to the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary,</hi> and other <hi>Saints,</hi> as well as to <hi>GOD and our Saviour,</hi> you do not believe many thouſands in our Communion, either through groſs <hi>Ignorance,</hi> ſome fond <hi>Opinions,</hi> or an exceſſive and <hi>extravagant Devotion,</hi> are not hugely guilty of <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry?</hi> And whether in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> this is not laying <hi>Snares,</hi> and digging <hi>Pits</hi> for human Souls?</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether theſe Paſſages and Expreſſions which I have cited out of our <hi>Offices, Breviaries,</hi> and other <hi>allow'd</hi> Books of <hi>Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> do not abundantly prove that we <hi>Catholicks</hi> do horribly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the <hi>Bounds and Rules</hi> which the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux,</hi> and our <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> ſet us about <hi>Praying to Saints,</hi> &amp;c. And in good earneſt, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Is it not manifeſt that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100283:15"/>we addreſs our ſelves to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> in the ſame <hi>manner and words,</hi> as unto <hi>GOD,</hi> and <hi>directly</hi> ask of her, thoſe <hi>Gifts and Graces, Good Things,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Bleſſings, which none but <hi>GOD</hi> can give? Do not we expreſs as much <hi>trust, hope, and confidence</hi> in her, as 'tis poſſible for Men by Words to expreſs to GOD, and our B. Saviour? Would not the very ſame words, which are here us'd to her, ſerve to ſignifie the greateſt <hi>ſence, awe,</hi> and <hi>reverence,</hi> and to offer up the greateſt and moſt <hi>paſſionate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires</hi> of our Souls to <hi>GOD,</hi> and our dear <hi>Saviour,</hi> only changing <hi>Lady</hi> into <hi>Lord, Mother</hi> into <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>ſweeteſt, bleſſed glorious Virgin,</hi> into <hi>ſweeteſt, bleſſed, and glorious GOD, and Saviour?</hi> And is this in good truth no more than a <hi>manner</hi> of Praying? Do men upon Earth thus pray for one another, or deſire others to pray for them? And is it no more than to fay, <hi>Pray for us?</hi> What Wit of Man, and without doing open violence to the plain and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſenſe of Words, is able to reconcile our <hi>Church</hi> to herſelf, or theſe <hi>Prayers</hi> to this Form, <hi>Pray for us?</hi> And is there not here downright ſaying, <hi>Have mercy upon us, hear us?</hi> And is not this giving to the <hi>Saints</hi> what is proper to GOD? What man in his <hi>Senſes</hi> ever pray'd in this manner to his <hi>abſent, or preſent Friends, or Brethren upon Earth?</hi> What <hi>ſick Mon,</hi> that was not alſo abſolutely <hi>Diſtracted</hi> ever thus deſir'd, either his <hi>Friend,</hi> or the <hi>Congregation</hi> to pray for him? Or whoever yet pray'd to his <hi>Friend,</hi> or his <hi>Brethren,</hi> or to any <hi>Congregation</hi> upon Earth, thus, <q>O Sacred Majeſty and Soveraign Lord, of <hi>Unlimited</hi> Power, <hi>Most</hi> merciful Brother, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Only</hi> hope of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, admit me into the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> of your Audience. I fly unto your Protection, for I have this <hi>Only</hi> Refuge, to caſt my ſelf under the ſhadow of your Wings; I rely on the Bowels of your <hi>Mercy</hi> in <hi>all</hi> my Wants Petitions, and Tribulations of Body and Mind; deſpiſe not my Prayers in my Neceſſities, but deliver me from <hi>all Dangers.</hi> Grant me <hi>Grace,</hi> that I may receive pardon for my Sins; drive away all Sins from me; make me <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>chaſt,</hi> and give me purity of Life; make my Heart to burn with Love to Chriſt; let all that is due unto me for my Sins, be cancell'd by your <hi>Merits;</hi> let the greatneſs of your <hi>Mercy</hi> blot out the multitude of mine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences; turn not away your face from me, for my truſt is in you. What can I do without you? Or what would become of me if you ſhould turn away your face from me? If you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100283:16"/>ſhould have forſaken me, to whom ſhould I then have repair'd, that would have lookt upon me with pity and compaſſion? O, our moſt kind <hi>Brother, Command, Compel</hi> GOD to have Mercy upon me a Sinner; protect me from the Enemy, receive me at the hour of Death; give me a ſafe paſſage into the next World; receive my Soul into your hands, when it ſhall leave this Mortal Body; take it into your Protection, and give it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Paradiſe and defend me in the Day of Judgment.</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>V. <hi>Open my Lips, O dear</hi> Friend, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>R. <hi>And my Soul ſhall ſpeak forth thy Praiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>V. Divine Friend, <hi>&amp;c. be intent to my Aid;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>R. <hi>Graciouſly make haſt to help me.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>V. <hi>Glory be to</hi> Jeſus <hi>and my</hi> Friend, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>R. <hi>As it was, is, and ever ſhall be.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Now <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> deal plainly with me, Does not this ſort of Prayer, thus offer'd to a <hi>Creature,</hi> make even <hi>You</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with horror? And yet it is every word taken out of theſe <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> and <hi>Books</hi> I have but juſt now quoted? Tell me then ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, I beſeech you, Was ever ſuch a <hi>Prayer</hi> made by any Perſon well or <hi>ſick,</hi> that was in his Senſes, either to his <hi>Friend,</hi> his <hi>Brethren,</hi> or any <hi>Congregation</hi> upon Earth? Or is ſuch a Prayer fit to be made to any of them? Nay, I ask, Is ſuch a <hi>Prayer</hi> fit to be made to any <hi>Saint</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> or to the <hi>B. Virgin</hi> herſelf? Nay farther, Ought we, or is it poſſible, for us to Addreſs our ſelves to <hi>GOD,</hi> and our <hi>B. Saviour,</hi> in any <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> or <hi>Words,</hi> more ſuitable to that <hi>Soveraign Being,</hi> and our dependance on him? And laſtly, What greater things can be ſaid to the Eternal and ever Bleſſed <hi>Trinity?</hi> With what face then do we maintain againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that we do not Pray to the <hi>Saints</hi> as unto <hi>GOD,</hi> nor ask thoſe things of them, which ought only to be ask'd of <hi>GOD,</hi> and our <hi>Saviour,</hi> becauſe they only can give them? And that we only pray to them, as one Friend deſires another upon Earth. And with what Juſtice do we of late complain of them, for charging us with theſe <hi>Practices,</hi> and would make the <hi>World</hi> believe that they <hi>Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> us? When it is plain, that we are highly guilty of them, and are our ſelves indeed the very <hi>Miſrepreſenters?</hi> For the Love of <hi>GOD,</hi> our own and our Neighbours <hi>Souls,</hi> Why ſhould
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100283:16"/>we any longer <hi>palliate and diſguiſe</hi> the matter, or by any means defend a <hi>Worſhip,</hi> for which we can ſhew no Law of <hi>GOD,</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> and which by our own confeſſion is very apt to betray Men into theſe heinous Sins of <hi>Superſtition and Idolatry?</hi> Why ſhould we, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> any longer wrong our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and deceive the World, in ſo important a matter, meerly to ſupport the <hi>vile Worldly Interest</hi> and Honour of a <hi>Church,</hi> that's afraid to confeſs herſelf in an Error. Becauſe for <hi>baſe ends,</hi> ſhe once aſſum'd the Title of <hi>Infallible?</hi> Without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> would it not be more for the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>good and ſecurity</hi> of <hi>Souls,</hi> not only to condemn and lay aſide theſe, but <hi>all Prayers</hi> whatever to <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and ingenuouſly confeſs, that in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular however, we have been in an <hi>Error,</hi> and the <hi>Reformed</hi> in the <hi>right?</hi> And that it is abundantly <hi>ſufficient</hi> for <hi>Salvation</hi> to pray to <hi>GOD alone,</hi> through the <hi>Merits, Mediation,</hi> and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion only of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> our Bleſſed <hi>Redeemer,</hi> becauſe GOD has commanded no more? And if neither our <hi>Church,</hi> nor you for her, will acknowledge an <hi>Error</hi> in ſo plain a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and of ſuch vaſt concern, muſt not we needs be thought People of a <hi>monſtrous</hi> Courage, to truſt our own Souls, and the Souls of our Children in ſuch a <hi>Church,</hi> and in the hands of ſuch <hi>Guides?</hi> Again, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What ſignifies it with the Biſhop of <hi>Meaux, in the Fourth Section of his Expoſition,</hi> to ſay, <hi>That in what Terms ſoever thoſe Prayers which we Addreſs to Saints, are couch'd, it is the</hi> Intention <hi>of the Church, and of her Faithful, to reduce them always to this form, Pray for us?</hi> Can the <hi>Intention of the Church, and of her Faithful,</hi> alter the nature of things, and the univerſal meaning of plain words? or is any ſuch declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Intention</hi> to be admitted againſt the <hi>plain, literal, and gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical</hi> Sence of the Prayers? But if the Sence and <hi>Intention</hi> of the Church, be no more, than to <hi>Pray for us,</hi> then why are not the <hi>Prayers and Hymns</hi> in our <hi>Publik Offices, Breviaries,</hi> &amp;c. at leaſt, alter'd to the Sence and <hi>Intention</hi> of our Church? And why are any other <hi>Books of Devotion</hi> ſuffer'd to come out, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Sence and <hi>Intention</hi> of the Church? What a ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous proceeding, to ſay no worſe of it, is this of our <hi>Church,</hi> both to compoſe and ſet out <hi>Prayers to the Saints</hi> herſelf, and alſo permit others to do ſo too, <hi>couch'd</hi> and expreſs'd in ſuch <hi>Words, Titles,</hi> and <hi>Phraſes,</hi> as all ſenſible Mankind make uſe of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100283:17"/>to expreſs their Thoughts and Deſires in their Prayers to <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Holy <hi>Trinity</hi> and then cry out, <hi>That in what terms ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, thoſe Prayers which we make to the Saints, are couch'd, it is the Intention of the Church,</hi> &amp;c. Is the <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, or any <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> Language, ſo barren of <hi>Words,</hi> that when our Church would <hi>Invocate the Saints and Angels,</hi> &amp;c. ſhe can do it in no other <hi>manner, words,</hi> or <hi>terms,</hi> than ſuch in which ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and <hi>properly</hi> addreſſes herſelf to <hi>GOD,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Trinity?</hi> Are there not in every Language, and particularly in ours, <hi>apt and proper</hi> words and terms in which to expreſs our Souls to <hi>GOD</hi> and the <hi>Holy Trinity?</hi> And likewiſe when we would deſire the <hi>Saints and Angels to Pray for us?</hi> What folly as well as wickedneſs is it then to confound theſe <hi>Objects</hi> ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly different, in the ſame <hi>terms</hi> and <hi>words,</hi> and to uſe thoſe to the <hi>Saints and Angels,</hi> which are proper to GOD only? Again, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Do not Men generally underſtand words as they ſound and uſually ſignifie? And does not the very natural ſence of words, raiſe proper and ſuitable <hi>Ideas</hi> in Mens minds? Now I would fain know of you, <hi>Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> What Thoughts or <hi>Idea's</hi> a Man can be ſuppos'd to have, who after this <hi>manner,</hi> and for theſe things, thus addreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the <hi>Virgin Mary?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Sacred Majeſty, Mother of <hi>Unlimited</hi> Power, the <hi>only</hi> hope of Sinners, ador'd and call'd upon by the whole Univerſe, and who by innumerable Titles claim the <hi>Utmost</hi> Duty of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian, as a <hi>Proper Homage</hi> to your Greatneſs. Let the greatneſs of your <hi>Mercy</hi> blot out the multitude of mine Offences, and deliver me from all Dangers. I entruſt you with whatever I am, have, do, or hope in Life and Death, and through all Eternity. I own my ſelf in your Preſence, and that you ſurvey the preſent ſtate of my Soul, all my Thoughts and Projects, and every tract of my Converſation, and therefore I put my ſelf wholly under your Protection, and will obſerve you as my <hi>Soveraign</hi> Lady, relying on your Bowels of Mercy in all my Wants of Body and Mind. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me from the Enemy, and when my Soul departs from my Body,</q> receive it into the Glory of Paradice, &amp;c. Now do ye think, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> that Invocating the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> in ſuch words as theſe, would not make any Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men very apt to entertain ſuch an Idea of her as is only fit and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100283:17"/>proper to be thought of GOD? Would not the continual uſe of ſuch a Prayer, make a man inſenſibly to forget, eſpecially in the act and heat of Devotion, that ſhe is but a Creature? and fancy that he is a praying to ſome <hi>Being</hi> of <hi>Divine Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Perfections?</hi> Would not the <hi>interior Sentiments</hi> of his Mind think ye, grow like his <hi>exterior Words and Expreſſions,</hi> when in any Publick Place of Divine Worſhip, or but in his Cloſet, he is upon his <hi>Knees with Hands and Eyes lifted up,</hi> and in a perfect poſture of <hi>Adoration?</hi> But if ſuch a Man ſhould not inſenſibly, by the meer force of uſing ſuch Words and Expreſſions, fall into the thoughts of her being a <hi>GOD,</hi> and ſo be guilty of <hi>flat Idolatry;</hi> yet can you deny, that he is upon the very brink of that Danger? And muſt it not be eſteem'd a <hi>Miracle,</hi> if ſuch a Perſon is preſerv'd from falling into that Precipice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> II. But, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I am not ignorant that our <hi>Diſputers</hi> think they ſufficiently clear their hands of ſuch Writers, as the Author of the <hi>Contemplation,</hi> &amp;c. Father <hi>Craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,</hi> Cardinals <hi>Bona and Bonaventure, Bernardin de Buſts,</hi> &amp;c. by ſaying that ſuch things as they teach, and ſuch <hi>Prayers</hi> and Expreſſions, as they compoſe and publiſh, are not the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Practices</hi> of our Church, but the <hi>extravagant Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Flights of Devotion of ſome particular Men.</hi> Now that this <hi>Plea</hi> has no place, and is of no force againſt ſuch Prayers as are found in the <hi>Offices, Breviaries, Miſſals,</hi> &amp;c. of our <hi>Church,</hi> I humbly conceive you'll eaſily grant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ſuch <hi>Prayers,</hi> and that <hi>ſtrange</hi> Language and Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons found in them, muſt unavoidably be charg'd upon our <hi>Church.</hi> But then concerning theſe others, I humbly enquire, Why the <hi>Church</hi> (if your <hi>Order, Reverend Fathers,</hi> be a part of the <hi>Church</hi>) allows and permits ſuch, in particular, the <hi>Contemplations,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Father Craſſet's Book?</hi> and the ſame I might ask concerning the other Authors I have but now nam'd, for I am told they are all publiſh'd by the Authority of the Church, or by the <hi>permiſſion</hi> of thoſe appointed by the <hi>Church.</hi> And does not ſuch permiſſion amount to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches <hi>approbation?</hi> And does the Church uſe to approve of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, that is not the Doctrine of the <hi>Church?</hi> And if it be the Doctrine of our Church, Why do ye not ſpeak out, and declare ſo, and prove it to be the Doctrine of <hi>Christ</hi> and his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100283:18"/>
                  <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> But if you ſtill deny it to be the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> then pray. Why are not the Books call'd in, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, and forbid to be read, and the Men who writ them puniſht for <hi>Falſe Teachers,</hi> and <hi>Deceivers?</hi> Again, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> if ſuch be not the Doctrine of our Church, as I would now fain hope, for a very material reaſon, it is not, then pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> let me humbly ask you again. Why are theſe Books let alone to deceive our poor <hi>ignorant People</hi> into ſuch groſs Errors? And here alſo it will be perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to <hi>enquire</hi> of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Why ſuch <hi>Books</hi> as corrupt the Doctrines of <hi>Repentance,</hi> and deſtroy the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Holy Life, <hi>ſpeaking Truth,</hi> and <hi>doing Juſtice,</hi> and in a word, all the <hi>Moral</hi> Duties and Practice of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> are permitted to walk freely and boldly abroad in the <hi>World,</hi> and debauch Mens Principles and Practices? Why are they not, I ſay, call'd in, or forbid, or the Doctrines by the higheſt <hi>Authority</hi> condemn'd, and the <hi>Authors,</hi> who are alive, ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſht? A Collection of theſe Doctrines. I am told, is made by one, or more, of the Doctors of <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> (who are eſteem'd by moſt wiſe and good Men, as <hi>Orthodon Catholicks</hi> as any) and is Entituled, <hi>The Morals of</hi> your Society. Now, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> to a Man that is never ſo little touch'd with the <hi>true ſpirit of a Chriſtian,</hi> muſt it not needs be a ſad conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, to think how many poor ignorant People in our Communion, fall into the miſery of ſuch <hi>Guides?</hi> And ought not this to make all us <hi>Catholicks,</hi> very careful and cautious about the choice of our <hi>Spiritual Guides</hi> and <hi>Ghoſtly Fathers,</hi> ſince it ſeems there are ſo many in <hi>our Church,</hi> that if we fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd them, would lead us into ſuch pernitious and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Errors? And here upon this conſideration, I cannot omit, in this place, enquiring of you, and I humbly beg you to give me a particular anſwer to it. What ſignifies it to us ignorant <hi>Lay</hi> People, whether the <hi>Pope</hi> or a <hi>General</hi> Council, or <hi>both</hi> together be <hi>Infallible,</hi> if the Pariſh-<hi>Priest, Fryar,</hi> or <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> who has the management of our Souls, be not Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo? For ſince he is our <hi>immediate</hi> Teacher, and not the General <hi>Council,</hi> nor the <hi>Pope,</hi> is it not plain, that if he ſhould be either a <hi>Fool</hi> or a <hi>Knave,</hi> he may either through <hi>ignorance,</hi> or to ſerve ſome <hi>carnal</hi> and worldly Intereſt, lead us into damnable Errors? I could be much larger in my Thoughts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100283:18"/>on this Enquiry; but I conſider that I may have a fitter oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for it, and therefore ſhall make no further digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> III. But, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I muſt needs yet be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with you, and tell you, That whether ſuch things as Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Bonaventare,</hi> and others have taught about the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> be, or be not the Doctrine of our Church, I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs infinitely diſturb'd in my mind. If what <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> has writ be not the Doctrine of our <hi>Church,</hi> then I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſcandaliz'd that our Church ſhould <hi>Canonize</hi> for a <hi>Saint,</hi> a Perſon guilty of ſuch horrid and blaſphemous Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And then again, ſuppoſe you could ſatisfie me (which I fear you cannot) that our Church has actually condemn'd theſe Books and Writings of his, and others, yet certainly, is it not a moſt dangerous thing to be in our <hi>Communion,</hi> where ſuch <hi>Spiritual Guides</hi> are ſo frequent? <hi>Lord!</hi> ſay I to myſelf, what a deal of miſchief may they do, and how many Souls may they poyſon and ruin eternally, before their damnable <hi>Errors</hi> and pernicious Doctrines are diſcover'd and condemn'd? Whatever you may think on't, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I do profeſs that I am deeply ſenſible, that we <hi>Catholicks</hi> run a deſperate hazard in the choice and uſe of our <hi>Spiritual Guides.</hi> And does not this frequency of <hi>Falſe Teachers</hi> among us, make it highly reaſonable and neceſſary, that we People ſhould have the <hi>liberty to examine</hi> their Doctrines, whether true or falſe? And if we muſt examine them, as I do not ſee but we are bound, unleſs you can prove, that we muſt <hi>blindly</hi> follow our <hi>Guides,</hi> then I deſire to know of you, By what <hi>Rule,</hi> and by what <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Faculties?</hi> Surely, there is not only ſome certain <hi>Rule,</hi> but ſome certain <hi>means</hi> to uſe that <hi>Rule</hi> by in our Church, for us <hi>Lay</hi> People, or elſe to what purpoſe is the <hi>liberty</hi> you give us of <hi>examining and trying your Doctrines?</hi> But I fancy I may have room to make a particular <hi>Enquiry</hi> concerning this matter, and therefore ſhall ſtep no farther from my preſent ſubject.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IV. But, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> the two words <hi>Command,</hi> and <hi>Compel,</hi> which our <hi>Cardinal,</hi> and <hi>Saint Bonaventure</hi> us'd in his <hi>Orizon</hi> to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and quoted in the Firſt Query of this Section, are ſo exceſſive harſh and horrid, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100283:19"/>I could not forbear enquiring of you, Whether theſe Words do not with a witneſs, <hi>elevate the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>above the condition of a Creature,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Expoſition, Sect. 4. <hi>p.</hi> 7.</note> which yet the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Meanx</hi> is ſo <hi>modest</hi> to ſay our Church does not? And does it not only make her <hi>equal,</hi> but alſo, ſet her infinitly above <hi>GOD</hi> her <hi>Creator?</hi> Unleſs that Perſon who <hi>Commands,</hi> and <hi>Compels,</hi> be <hi>inferior</hi> to the Perſon <hi>Commanded,</hi> and <hi>Compelld?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> V. If I miſtake not, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> we account the <hi>Roſary</hi> a ſpecial Piece of Devotion, and great things are ſaid of its <hi>effects,</hi> by many of our <hi>Eminent</hi> Writers, and Guides in Devotion. Now I will not at preſent enquire into theſe things, nor into the great <hi>Myſteries</hi> ſaid to be in it, but will only humbly ask you, 1. What Antiquity, or what Reaſon can you ſhew for turning the <hi>Angel's Salutation of the Virgin Mary,</hi> into a <hi>direct Prayer</hi> to her? Did the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſay, <hi>Holy Mother of GOD, pray for us Sinners, now, and in the Hour of Death;</hi> if the Angel did not, How comes it to be <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent</hi> for us to do it? But, 2. What is the true reaſon, that in the <hi>Roſary</hi> we are to ſay Ten <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> to One <hi>Pater No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?</hi> I have often askt this Queſtion of ſome of our Prieſts, but could never get a ſatisfactory Anſwer. Now if in this matter I had Courage enough to follow my <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I profeſs, I think, I ſhould ſay <hi>Ten Pater Noſters, to One Ave Marie.</hi> For ſeriouſly, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> has not <hi>GOD</hi> given us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably far greater Evidence both of his <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> than ever the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> did? 3. Why do our <hi>Preachers</hi> immediately before their <hi>Sermons,</hi> ſay an <hi>Ave Marie?</hi> Why do they addreſs themſelves to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion? Is ſhe the Fountain and Giver of all <hi>good and perfect Gifts?</hi> Does Wiſdom and Eloquence come from her? Would it not, think ye, be far more decent and reaſonable to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to <hi>GOD,</hi> or to the <hi>Holy Ghost,</hi> at ſuch a time? But after all, What <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Antiquity</hi> can you produce for this ſtrange <hi>Practice?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VI. Can you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> prove by <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi>'s Rule, that departed <hi>Souls</hi> do enjoy Beatifical Viſion before the Day of Judgment? If you can, I humbly beg you would do it. As alſo, that the <hi>Saints</hi> departed do cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly hear our Prayers. You perceive well enough, I doubt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100283:19"/>not, why I make this <hi>Enquiry.</hi> For if the departed <hi>Saints</hi> neither enjoy <hi>Beatifical Viſion,</hi> nor <hi>hear</hi> our Prayers, Is it not yet more abſurd for us to pray to them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VII. I think that we aſſert, that all <hi>Certainty</hi> in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Religion</hi> muſt be <hi>Infallible,</hi> or elſe it is nothing worth, becauſe we can never rely upon it. Now, pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What <hi>Infallible Aſſurance</hi> have we <hi>Catholicks,</hi> that all thoſe who are <hi>Canoniz'd Saints</hi> by his <hi>Holineſs,</hi> are indeed <hi>Saints,</hi> and in <hi>Heaven?</hi> If we have not <hi>Infallible Aſſurance,</hi> what reaſon have we Religiouſly to <hi>Invocate</hi> them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VIII. Our <hi>Repreſenter,</hi> p. 4. diſtinguiſhes between <hi>Mediators</hi> of <hi>Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Mediators</hi> of <hi>Interceſſion;</hi> of this laſt, he ſays, <hi>He does not at all doubt, but 'tis acceptable with GOD we ſhould have many.</hi> Now here I humbly enquire of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> From whom he learnt this <hi>Diſtinction?</hi> From <hi>GOD,</hi> or from Man? if from <hi>GOD,</hi> Should he not prove it from <hi>Scripture?</hi> And how can he do it, ſince it is there ſo plainly reveal'd, that <hi>GOD</hi> hath appointed the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator</hi> of <hi>Redemption,</hi> to be alſo our <hi>Mediator</hi> of <hi>Interceſſion,</hi> and that his <hi>Interceſſion</hi> is grounded upon his <hi>Redemption:</hi> thus <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> chap. 7. ver. 25. <hi>Whereby he is able to ſave alſo for ever, them that go by himſelf to God, always living to make interceſſion for us:</hi> and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> chap. 2. ver. 5, 6. <hi>For there is one God, one alſo mediator of God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus: who gave himſelf a redemption for all.</hi> Now, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Can you ſhew me ſuch another Text for the <hi>Saints</hi> being our <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators</hi> of <hi>Interceſſion?</hi> But if you ſay this Diſtinction is from Man, then I deſire to know, How any Man, or all the Men upon Earth, came by ſuch an Authority, as to appoint any <hi>Mediators</hi> with <hi>GOD,</hi> beſides himſelf? And laſtly, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Can you ſhew from <hi>Univerſal Antiquity,</hi> that the <hi>Saints</hi> departed, are by <hi>GOD,</hi> appointed <hi>Mediators</hi> of <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi> as well as the Man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> If you can, I deſire you to do it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IX. Pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> upon what Ground or Authority does our Church diſtribute the <hi>Patronage</hi> of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>Countries,</hi> the <hi>Cure</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> and the <hi>Protection</hi> of all diſtinct <hi>Profeſſions</hi> of Men, and all kinds of Creatures to particular <hi>Saints?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> X. Why, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> are there in <hi>Catholick</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100283:20"/>Countries, as <hi>Italy, Spain,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> more <hi>Churches</hi> built, more <hi>Altars</hi> erected, more <hi>Preſents</hi> made, and more <hi>Coſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd, more <hi>Prayers</hi> pour'd out, and <hi>Vows</hi> made, and <hi>Offices</hi> perform'd to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> who is but a Creature after all, than to our Dear <hi>Saviour,</hi> who is <hi>GOD the Creator?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XI. I am told, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> That towards the latter end of the Fourth <hi>Century,</hi> a certain <hi>Sect</hi> of Women did appear, which met together, to offer certain <hi>Cakes,</hi> and otherwiſe to Worſhip the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which Cakes were call'd <hi>Collyrides,</hi> and the Women from them <hi>Collyridians:</hi> and that the good Biſhop, St. <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> did write zealouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and treated them as <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Let</hi> Mary <hi>be honour'd, but the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</hi> Now, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I deſire to know of you, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this is true? and, Whether we do not offer <hi>Candles and Incenſe</hi> to the <hi>Virgin Mary?</hi> And if thoſe Women were <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> for offering Cakes to her, Pray what are we for offering up to her Candles? Pray where's the difference between <hi>Cakes</hi> and <hi>Candles,</hi> as to their being made an <hi>Offering?</hi> Does not this Example abundantly Confute thoſe Men, who ſay, It is impoſſible that any now ſhould be ſo ſottiſh to make a <hi>GOD</hi> of her, and Worſhip her with that Worſhip which is due to <hi>GOD only?</hi> For if there were People ſo groſly ſilly to commit Idolatry about her, Pray why not much rather now? Are not the preſent allow'd <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable enough to draw People into the like Crime? And are there not both Women and Men too, in this Age, of as weak Underſtandings, and of as <hi>Superſtitious and Idolatrous</hi> Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as then?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XII. I am told, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> that the aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd Cardinal <hi>Bona,</hi> in his ſaid Book, Entituled, <hi>Horolog. Aſcet.</hi> tells us, That the <hi>Roſary</hi> is ſo call'd, becauſe 'tis Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of <hi>One Hundred and Fifty Ave Maries, as of ſo many ſweet-ſmelling Roſes:</hi> Now I humbly beg of you to know the true reaſon, Why the <hi>Ave Maries</hi> are <hi>Roſes</hi> rather, and ſmell ſweeter, than the <hi>Pater Noſters?</hi> When a Man reflects, that the <hi>Pater Noſters</hi> are of our dear <hi>Lord's</hi> own compoſing, he is apt to think, that they might deſerve the name of Roſes as well, and ſmell, at leaſt as ſweet as the <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> the one being a <hi>ſolemn Prayer</hi> contriv'd and dictated by the <hi>Eternal</hi> Wiſdom, for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100283:20"/>the needs and benefit of his poor Creatures, and the other only a common <hi>Form</hi> of one <hi>Creature's Saluting</hi> another, and which by I know not what authority, nor with what pertinency, is ſince converted into a <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Religious Prayer.</hi> And do not you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally think, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> that this magnifying the Excellency, and the Odour of the <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> above the <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> is not, to ſpeak ſoftly, a little contrary to the Laws of Good Manners?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XIII. Whether the <hi>Honour</hi> that is due to a glorified <hi>Soul,</hi> ought to be any more than that of <hi>Love or Charity, Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Imitation?</hi> And whether in our allow'd <hi>Prayers,</hi> &amp;c. we do not give to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and other <hi>Saints,</hi> that of <hi>Service</hi> as to our <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters?</hi> And whether that <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Reſpect</hi> that is to be given to a <hi>Saint,</hi> or an <hi>Angel,</hi> or an <hi>Image,</hi> muſt not be ſuch as is proper to a <hi>Saint,</hi> or an <hi>Angel,</hi> or an <hi>Image,</hi> and not <hi>Worſhip</hi> or <hi>Adoration?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XIV. Whether the <hi>Common</hi> People underſtand the nice <hi>Scholaſtical</hi> Diſtinctions, and Degrees of <hi>Divine Honour and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> which 'tis ſaid our cunning <hi>Doctors,</hi> and ſubtil <hi>School-men</hi> have devis'd to excuſe our Doctrines and Practices from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Latria, Dulia,</hi> and <hi>Hyperdulia?</hi> As you hope to be ſaved, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Do you believe that the more <hi>ignorant</hi> Men and Women, nay, the more <hi>knowing</hi> Perſons, when they are in the Act of <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Adoration,</hi> do, or can make uſe of theſe nice and learned <hi>Diſtinctions,</hi> and make this juſt ſeparation in their minds? And <hi>yet</hi> if they do not, is not their falling into <hi>Idolatry</hi> unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? To what fatal Dangers are we poor <hi>Catholicks</hi> expos'd!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> XV. But to conclude this matter of <hi>Invocation,</hi> &amp;c. I far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquire of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Whether you can ſhew any footeſteps of <hi>Prayers to Saints,</hi> for the firſt 300 years (I have heard that ſome Learned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> dare give you 350 years) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in any genuine <hi>Father,</hi> or publick <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Liturgy?</hi> If it had been the Doctrine and Practice of that time as 'tis now among us, can it enter into any but a mad Mans head, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it would not be found either in ſome publick <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Liturgy,</hi> or in ſome of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> in that compaſs of time? And if we cannot make it appear to have been the Doctrine and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in all that time, for God's ſake, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What reaſon have we to make ſuch a conſiderable <hi>addition</hi> to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Ages?</hi> Why may not we be ſaved now without it, as well as the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> then? But, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I am
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100283:21"/>farther told, which in my mind is an invincible argument againſt us in this affair, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have made it plainly appear from the Writings of the <hi>Ancient</hi> Fathers, both <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern,</hi> by the <hi>Greek Canon,</hi> the <hi>Liturgies,</hi> father'd upon St. <hi>James</hi> and the other <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Liturgies</hi> of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Egypt</hi> attributed to St. <hi>Baſil, Gregory Nazianzen,</hi> and St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> and that of St. <hi>Chyſoſtom,</hi> and by the <hi>Mozarabical Office</hi> us'd in <hi>Spain,</hi> that whereas we <hi>now</hi> Pray <hi>To,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians then</hi> Pray'd <hi>For</hi> the Souls of the <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets, Martyrs, Confeſſors, Preachers, Evangeliſts,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all the Souls of the <hi>Juſt</hi> which died in the <hi>Faith,</hi> but chiefly for the <hi>Holy, Glorious, and Perpetual Virgin Mary, the Mother of GOD.</hi> Now I deſire to know of you, Whether any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writer has done this? or whether it is true or falſe? But if theſe things are true, and can be made appear, as I am pretty ſure they can, then I deſire to know, Whether the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> cannot with great Truth and Juſtice make theſe Concluſions upon us, 1. That our Church and People now <hi>prays,</hi> and makes their <hi>Confeſſion To</hi> thoſe <hi>very depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Souls, For</hi> which the ancient <hi>Chriſtians</hi> pray'd. 2. That the Prayers which were <hi>then</hi> in uſe, were for ſuch Perſons as by the confeſſion, even of our ſelves, never were in <hi>Purgatory:</hi> for who among us dare ſay, that the Soul of the B. <hi>Virgin</hi> ever was in <hi>Purgatory?</hi> 3. That the Ancients Practice of praying for the <hi>Dead,</hi> does not at all prove their belief of a <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and that there may be Prayers for the <hi>Dead,</hi> and yet no <hi>Purgatory.</hi> 4. That the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of thoſe Times did not believe the <hi>Saints departed</hi> enjoy'd <hi>Beatifical Viſion,</hi> and ſo to be ſure did not pray to them. For is it not a little too groſs to think of them, that if they had believ'd the <hi>Saints</hi> enjoy'd <hi>Beatifical Viſion,</hi> they would ſtill pray <hi>for</hi> them? And if they had believ'd that the <hi>Saints</hi> did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy <hi>Beatifical Viſion,</hi> is it not to treat them like <hi>Mad-folks,</hi> to think they would pray to them. And, 5. and laſtly, May not all this be allow'd to make up a <hi>Demonſtration,</hi> that at leaſt, in theſe <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> and the belief of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> &amp;c. our <hi>Faith, Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> are quite contrary to the <hi>Firſt Chriſtians?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100283:21"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> I. PRay, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What is that <hi>lawful Uſe of,</hi> and <hi>due Honour and Veneration,</hi> which the Council of <hi>Trent, Seſſion</hi> 25, ſays, Ought, and is to be given, <hi>to the Images and Relicks of Chriſt and the Saints?</hi> Wherein does it conſiſt? And by what acts, words, and ſigns, is it to be ſignify'd and expreſs'd? Is it the ſame that is due to Chriſt and the Saints, or is it ſome other different from that? Whether theſe words of the <hi>Council (Lawful and Due)</hi> does not neceſſarily imply, that the <hi>People</hi> may be guilty of giving an <hi>unlawful,</hi> and an <hi>undue Honour and Veneration?</hi> and if ſo, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in does that conſiſt? And how may I know it to avoid it? Why was not the <hi>Council</hi> ſo <hi>kind</hi> and ſo <hi>honeſt</hi> to tell us, poor ignorant <hi>People,</hi> what was lawful and due, and what was not? Whether in your Conſcience you do not think, that in thoſe Countries where <hi>Catholicks</hi> have their full <hi>ſwing,</hi> and have a full liberty of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and no body to oppoſe and diſturb them with queſtions, as in <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> &amp;c. a great many ignorant People do not exceed in their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> and <hi>Veneration</hi> of <hi>Images</hi> and <hi>Relicks,</hi> and really give them what is <hi>unlawful</hi> and <hi>undue?</hi> And if ſo, may not a Man reaſonably doubt (eſpecially too, when he conſiders that the Fathers of this <hi>Council</hi> own'd, that great Abuſes were then crept into theſe Matters, and gave ſuch ſtrict Charge to the Biſhops to <hi>Inſtruct</hi> the People, leaſt they ſhould fall into dangerous Errors) that this Doctrine, and this <hi>Piece</hi> of <hi>Devotion</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> does very greatly tempt ignorant Men and Women to <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition?</hi> Beſides, I think, <hi>Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> you grant, that it is not a <hi>Duty</hi> commanded by <hi>GOD,</hi> Why then, ſince there is apparent danger in it for, and great Abuſes and Cheats practis'd by, thoſe of our <hi>Communion,</hi> and that it is a very great <hi>Block of Offence</hi> to the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> and hindrance to their being <hi>re-united</hi> to us, were it not infinitely better and wiſer of our <hi>Church,</hi> if ſhe entirely aboliſh'd it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> II. Whether more <hi>Reſpect,</hi> &amp;c. is not due to the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the meaneſt <hi>Beggar,</hi> than to all the <hi>Images,</hi> &amp;c. of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, or ten thouſand Saints, becauſe 'tis thought that the <hi>Poor</hi> are indeed the true <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Christ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> III. Whether it can be deny'd, that there have been <hi>Images and Pictures</hi> made to counterfeit Tears, Words, and Geſtures? Is it not highly ſuſpitious that the Churches connivance at them, at leaſt, was to induce filly People to believe there was ſomething of <hi>Divine</hi> in them, and to procure <hi>ſecular</hi> Honour and Advantage to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> &amp;c. If this was not the reaſon, I deſire to know, Why ſo long
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100283:22"/>they were conniv'd at, and ſuffer'd in many <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Countries?</hi> And whether the multitude of fictitious and falſe <hi>Relicks,</hi> the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitious <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Images</hi> of a <hi>falſe ſtamp,</hi> and the pretended <hi>New Miracles,</hi> make it not highly reaſonable for us <hi>Catholicks</hi> carefully to enquire into the truth of theſe things, before we admit and believe them? And ſince the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> in the ſame <hi>Seſſion</hi> ſpeaks of theſe kind of Abuſes, and gives charge about them, I deſire of you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> to know by what <hi>Infallible Rule</hi> we People muſt examine theſe matters, ſo as that we cannot poſſibly be deceiv'd with Counterfeits? And I humbly intreat you ſincerely to tell me, Whether theſe <hi>Tricks, Abuſes,</hi> and <hi>Cheats,</hi> were not at firſt brought in, and practiſed upon the <hi>Credulity</hi> of the poor ignorant and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious <hi>People,</hi> and afterwards kept and nouriſht by the <hi>Clergy,</hi> for <hi>diſhoneſt and baſe gain,</hi> as the aforeſaid <hi>Decree</hi> ſpeaks? And whether in theſe days we have not as much reaſon to queſtion the truth of <hi>Relicks, Images, Miracles,</hi> &amp;c. and diſhoneſt Practiſes and Deſigns, as they had in former times? And if we have not, I deſire you to aſſign me good ſubſtantial Reaſons for it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IV. I am told, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> that ſince the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> there's a new <hi>Pontifical,</hi> and in that a <hi>Form</hi> for a Solemn <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration</hi> of Images, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now I humbly enquire for the true reaſon, Why you <hi>Conſecrate,</hi> and make Prayers in the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of <hi>Images,</hi> and the <hi>Crucifix?</hi> Is not this a very fair way to induce <hi>ſilly</hi> and <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi> People, to believe there's after that, ſome ſort of Divinity in them, or ſome more than ordinary <hi>Preſence</hi> or <hi>Operation</hi> in, or by them? Elſe, pray tell me, Why many of us have a greater opinion of one <hi>Image,</hi> than of another of the ſame Perſon? and in one <hi>Place</hi> rather than in another? For inſtance, the <hi>Image</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> Why is it not as effectual and meritorious to Worſhip her before her <hi>Image</hi> at <hi>Montſerat,</hi> as at <hi>Mont-Aigu?</hi> and near at <hi>Home,</hi> as at <hi>Lorretto?</hi> Why do we go long and painful <hi>Pilgrimages</hi> to certain <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages</hi> at certain <hi>Places,</hi> if it is not, at leaſt, in hopes of being better heard, and finding more ſure relief for praying to, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of her there? Would not a wiſe Man be apt to think here's ſomething of <hi>Trick</hi> and <hi>Artifice</hi> in this <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice?</hi> But I humbly enquire of you, What is the true and honeſt account and reaſon of this whole Matter? What proof from <hi>Scripture,</hi> or what authority from prime <hi>Antiquity,</hi> for this Practice?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> V. Pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What's the meaning of that <hi>Prayer</hi> which the Biſhop uſes in Bleſſing, and Conſecrating a <hi>New Croſs,</hi> found in the <hi>Pontifical; viz.</hi>
                  <q>We pray thee, O Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that thou wouldſt vouchſafe to bleſs this <hi>Wood</hi> of thy Croſs, that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100283:22"/>it may be a wholſome Remedy to Mankind, a ſtability of Faith, an increaſe of Good Works, the Redemption of Souls, a comfort, protection and defence againſt the evil Darts of the Enemies, through our Lord, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi>
                  </q> And alſo of that <hi>Hymn</hi> or <hi>Prayer</hi> found in the <hi>Brev. Sab. ante Domin. Paſſ. &amp; Feſt. invent. Crucis. Hail, O Croſs, our only hope, increaſe Grace in the Godly, and blot out the Sins of the Guilty?</hi> I profeſs, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> theſe two Prayers infinitely trouble my mind: for I cannot for my life underſtand, but that we make the <hi>material Wooden</hi> Croſs an Object of Divine Worſhip, and directly pray unto it, or elſe that theſe Prayers are perfect nonfence. But be pleas'd to let me ask you a few Queſtions. After the Biſhop has pray'd, <hi>Bleſs this Wood,</hi> is the <hi>Croſs</hi> ſtill <hi>natural Wood,</hi> and the ſame it was before, or is its nature chang'd and alter'd? and is there ſome Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Excellency communicated to it? Elſe, What means theſe Words, <hi>Bleſs this Wood?</hi> Do we pray unto, and Worſhip <hi>this</hi> Croſs, or that on which our <hi>B. Saviour</hi> was Crucified? But let it be which it will, Is it not groſs <hi>Idolatry</hi> to make either of them the Object of <hi>Adoration,</hi> and directly to pray to either of them? If we ſay, that we do not pray to either of them, nor make either of them the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Adoration, but Jeſus <hi>Chriſt</hi> who ſuffre'd upon the <hi>Croſs,</hi> then where's the ſence of this Prayer, <hi>Bleſs this Wood,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Hail, O Croſs,</hi> &amp;c. What an unhappineſs is this! And would not any ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Man think the Compoſers of our Prayers, and the <hi>Church</hi> too, were both of them conſtantly <hi>infatuated,</hi> to make choice of ſuch Words and Expreſſions in their Prayers to <hi>GOD</hi> and our <hi>B. Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> that to take and underſtand them in the ſence and meaning of the Compoſers, and of the Church, we muſt do violence to all the Rules of Grammer, and to the plain and natural, and generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd ſence and meaning of Words and Speech?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VI. I enquire, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Whether our diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſaying we do not give Divine Worſhip <hi>terminatively,</hi> but <hi>relatively,</hi> and <hi>tranſiently,</hi> to a Crucifix or to <hi>Images,</hi> &amp;c. will ſave us from <hi>Idolatry,</hi> any more than it did the <hi>Heathens</hi> in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and wooden <hi>Images?</hi> And whether the ſame Plea, if it will excuſe us from groſs <hi>Idolatry,</hi> might not as well excuſe them? <hi>viz.</hi> That we do not Worſhip that <hi>Crucifix,</hi> or that Image, &amp;c. which we ſee and pray before, but him who ſuffer'd on't, or him whom it repreſents; ſo they, We do not Worſhip the <hi>Sun</hi> or this <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>Statue,</hi> but him who Created the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the Great <hi>GOD,</hi> by this <hi>Image,</hi> and this <hi>Statue?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100283:23"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> I. PRay, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What is the reaſon, why <hi>anciently</hi> the People of our <hi>Church</hi> us'd to pray thus, <hi>Grant unto us, O Lord, that this Oblation may profit the Soul of thy Servant</hi> Leo? And that afterwards this contrary Form was us'd, <hi>Grant unto us, O Lord, that by the Intereſt of thy Servant</hi> Leo, <hi>this Oblation may profit us?</hi> Was <hi>Leo</hi> one of our <hi>Popes,</hi> and a <hi>Saint</hi> in <hi>Purgatory</hi> when the firſt <hi>Form</hi> was us'd? And was he out of <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and in <hi>Heaven,</hi> when the Second <hi>Form</hi> was us'd? What Infallible Aſſurance have we, that any Soul is releas'd out of Purgatory, and in particular, that he is now out of Purgatory? And if we have not, How come we to uſe this laſt Form of Prayer? But pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> deal ingenuouſly with me, Do Glorious <hi>Saints,</hi> Canoniz'd and Reigning in Heaven, uſe to paſs through <hi>Purgatory</hi> fire? Was St. <hi>Monica,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in Purgatory? Can ye prove ſhe was there? Or do ye think, and can ye prove, that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> believ'd her there when he pray'd for her? And if ſhe was not in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> Does it not prove that the Ancients us'd to pray for the <hi>Dead,</hi> which yet they did not believe in <hi>Purgatory?</hi> Why then do we pray for none, but thoſe we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Purgatory? Where is our <hi>Conformity</hi> to the Belief and Practice of the <hi>Ancients</hi> in this matter?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> II. Does our Church, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> teach, That all <hi>Souls,</hi> none excepted, who are ſo happy to be ſaved, muſt, and do paſs through the Fire of <hi>Purgatory?</hi> If ſhe does, and likewiſe that our Prayers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do help them, How can we in Charity juſtifie our conſtant Cuſtom of not praying for the <hi>Departed Souls</hi> of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants?</hi> Do we believe that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> living and dying ſuch, are not finally ſaved, but damn'd? Does not this ſound harſh to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Charity? And does not this our neglect of offering up Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſaying <hi>Maſſes</hi> for their Souls, openly declare to the World our uncharitableneſs? And that we believe the Soul of every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon living and dying in the <hi>Reform'd Religion</hi> is damn'd? ſince we never fail of offering up <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Maſſes</hi> for thoſe Souls of whom we have the leaſt hope of Salvation?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> III. Do not you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> reckon the <hi>Reformed</hi> Religion to be <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> Why then do ye teach us to think and call it a <hi>New Religion?</hi> Are the Three <hi>Creeds,</hi> the Ten <hi>Commandments,</hi> the Lords <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the Holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New</hi> Teſtament, New? And yet I am pretty well aſſur'd theſe are the Foundation, and contain the whole of their <hi>Religion.</hi> Why then do ye ask them, and teach us to do ſo, <hi>Where was your Religion before</hi> Luther? Where's the Juſtice and the Truth of this? Is it not plain, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100283:23"/>
                  <hi>GOD</hi> and our <hi>B. Saviour</hi> are the Authors of this <hi>Religion?</hi> But, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What if they ſhould ask us, as ſometime I have been askt, without being able to anſwer a word, <hi>Where was your Religion before the Council of</hi> Trent? what ſhould I ſay? For my part, I have lookt till my eyes are weary, and cannot find a word, either in the Three <hi>Creeds,</hi> the Ten <hi>Commandments,</hi> the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> or the Holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that our Saviour has forbid us to Receive the Communion in Both Kinds; that the Bread and Wine, by Virtue of the Prieſt's ſaying, <hi>Hoc est,</hi> &amp;c. is tranſubſtantiated into the very natural Fleſh, Blood, Bones, and Sinews, and the Soul and Divinity of our Dear <hi>Saviour;</hi> that we muſt Pray to GOD in a Language we underſtand not; that <hi>Saints and Angels</hi> are to be Worſhipp'd with <hi>Religious</hi> Worſhip; that Mens Souls go to <hi>Purgatory,</hi> before they go to Heaven; that the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is Chriſt's Vicar; and that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is as Infallible as <hi>GOD;</hi> with many other Points, and Doctrines, too long here to be named at this time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IV. Pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> Had the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops and Paſtors in <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth's Reign, and at the time of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> by Virtue of their <hi>Ordination,</hi> &amp;c. receiv'd from <hi>Rome,</hi> Power and Authority to Preach and Teach the Truth of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Reform</hi> all Errors and Corruptions in Faith, Doctrines, Worſhip, and Manners, within their own Juriſdictions, Dioceſſes, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> If they had not, How were they <hi>God's Ambaſſadors,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Diſpenſers of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which is nothing elſe but Truth and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? If they had, and that the <hi>Reformed</hi> Faith, Doctrine, and Worſhip is the Truth of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> were not all our Forefathers in Conſcience bound to hearken to, and obey them; and not only for that reaſon, but alſo becauſe they were their <hi>Lawful Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Paſtors?</hi> And for the ſame reaſon are not we now bound to hearken to, and obey the preſent <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Paſtors</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who are their <hi>lawful</hi> and undoubted Succeſſors?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> V. Pray, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> What <hi>Council</hi> or <hi>Pope</hi> has declar'd and <hi>decreed</hi> againſt <hi>Rebellion,</hi> let one's Natural <hi>Prince</hi> be of what <hi>Religion</hi> he will, and never ſo contrary to the <hi>worldly</hi> Policy and Intereſt of <hi>Rome?</hi> I would fain hope, that you can ſatisfie me in this <hi>Enquiry,</hi> becauſe I have often heard our <hi>Church</hi> tax'd for a <hi>Diſloyal Church.</hi> But further I enquire, Whether no <hi>Council</hi> or Pope has ever declar'd and decreed, nor <hi>Cardinal,</hi> or <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> writ and maintain'd, That in many caſes, but eſpecially when <hi>Princes</hi> are not of the <hi>Religion</hi> and Intereſts of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is lawful to cut them off? And has there been no <hi>Treaſons</hi> committed, nor <hi>Rebellions</hi> acted, not only by the <hi>Laity,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and even by the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, in conformity and obedience to ſuch <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Doctrines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VI. What is the meaning I beſeech you, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> of that Book which is <hi>Intituled</hi> in <hi>Engliſh, The Tax of the Apoſtolick Chamber for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sins?</hi> The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> often upbraid us with it, and really I know not what to anſwer, becauſe I have enquir'd and find there is ſuch a <hi>Book,</hi> and more, that 'tis authoriz'd and allow'd by our <hi>Church.</hi> But I am much puzled to find out a good meaning of it. Methinks it ſounds a little harſh to Chriſtian ears, that for any ſums of <hi>money</hi> at all, there ſhould be, either <hi>Indulgence</hi> given to commit ſins, or a pardon procur'd after they are committed, and this Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh'd to all the <hi>World!</hi> Does not this look like <hi>tempting</hi> and inviting men to be <hi>wicked?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100283:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VII. If it be true, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> what the Proteſtants charge you, and the reſt of the <hi>Guides</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> with, as that you deny men the uſe of their <hi>Senſos</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> about Religion, and ſo would debaſe them into the condition of mere <hi>Brutes,</hi> is it not juſt to eſteem you the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Mankind? For to what end and purpoſe did <hi>God</hi> give us theſe <hi>Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties!</hi> was it only think ye to govern our ſelves in worldly affairs? And did not the wiſe and good <hi>God</hi> likewiſe endue us with <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that we might preſerve our ſelves from being <hi>impoſed upon</hi> and <hi>cheated</hi> by a falſe and <hi>abſurd</hi> Religion? Now what Deſign can that Man or Company of Men be rationally thought to have, who would rob <hi>Mankind</hi> of the only means which <hi>GOD</hi> has given them to preſerve themſelves from being <hi>deceiv'd</hi> in ſo mighty a Concernment as <hi>Religion?</hi> And from being made wretched <hi>Slaves,</hi> to wicked and <hi>deſigning</hi> Men? And on the contrary, Are not the <hi>Divines</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtant Churches</hi> to be highly <hi>valued and lov'd,</hi> becauſe they earneſtly invite Men to the Exerciſe of their <hi>Senſes</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> about <hi>Religion,</hi> and propound no Doctrines but what tends to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement and perfecting of <hi>Human,</hi> as well as <hi>Divine</hi> Knowledge, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobling the Nature of <hi>Man,</hi> which certainly is the Great Deſign of the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Religion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> VIII. Whether your way of conducting <hi>Religion,</hi> and managing <hi>Coneroverſies</hi> by Tricks and Arts, and expoſing the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, for the ſake of ſome unreaſonable Doctrines and Propofitions; by making <hi>Parallels</hi> between the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Firſt to depend only upon the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe the Second has no better Foundation. Is it not, I ſay, enough to ſet the Hearts of <hi>thinking</hi> Men againſt you?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quere</hi> IX. In the 22 <hi>Seſſion, Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>Of the Doctrine of the Sacrifice of the Maſs,</hi> the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> ſays, <hi>That although the Maſs contains a large Inſtruction of a Faithful People, yet it is not convenient to be exercis'd publickly in the Vulgar Tongue.</hi> How, <hi>Reverend Fathers! A large Inſtruction for the People,</hi> and yet not convenient to let the People underſtand it! Were not the Good <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> a little <hi>merry</hi> here, as well as myſterious? But pray be you pleas'd to be <hi>ſerious,</hi> and tell me, What do you think might be the true reaſon why theſe <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> Men thought it inconvenient to have <hi>Maſs</hi> ſaid in the <hi>Vulgar Tongue?</hi> Does it look kind and <hi>Chriſtian</hi>-Father-like, that altho' they confeſs the <hi>Maſs</hi> was a <hi>large Inſtruction for the People,</hi> yet that they ſhould at the ſame time Command to keep the People ignorant of it, except only ſome parcels of it, now and then to be dealt out to them? This manner of acting from <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Fathers to their Children, appears to me extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and therefore pray ſatisfie me about it, and tell me, what were they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of? And what inconvenience would have follow'd, ſuppoſe Maſs had been publickly ſaid, for example, in <hi>Engliſh?</hi> Why ſo much <hi>Policy</hi> and <hi>Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in our managing of <hi>Religion?</hi> I muſt needs tell you that I am ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd at it. For when a Man conſiders the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, he finds that certainly never was there a more <hi>plain, ſimple,</hi> and inartificial <hi>Religion</hi> than it. And ſince the wife <hi>GOD</hi> thought fit <hi>ſo</hi> to propound it to Mankind, how dare you and the reſt of the <hi>Paſtors,</hi> &amp;c. manage it like the <hi>Juggles and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100283:24"/>Intrigues</hi> of a <hi>State.</hi> Will not a ſerious <hi>Reflection</hi> on this, make thinking men apt to ſuſpect our <hi>Church</hi>-Governours and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Guides, and ſo by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the <hi>Doctrine and practices</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> too? And do ye think that wiſe men obſerving our <hi>Religion</hi> to be mixt with ſo much <hi>Craft</hi> and <hi>Worldly Policy,</hi> and that many of our <hi>Doctrines,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Purgatory</hi> and <hi>Indulgences,</hi> &amp;c. plainly tend to ſerve Worldly Ends, do not furniſh them with mighty Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices againſt our Church-men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query</hi> X. Whether, with wiſe and honeſt men, it is not, Reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> a vaſt and juſt prejudice againſt our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Cauſe,</hi> that our Writers of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie</hi> are ſo perpetually by the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Divines charg'd with uſing <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitious</hi> and <hi>Spurious</hi> Authors, and ſuch as the <hi>Honeſt and Learned</hi> men of our own <hi>Church</hi> diſallow of? And whether on the contrary, it is not both a good ſign, as well as a mighty credit and advantage for the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that its <hi>Defenders</hi> are never charg'd by us with alledging and quoting <hi>falſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit</hi> Authors, but can maintain their Cauſe againſt us by <hi>true and genuine</hi> Authors and Writings? Is not this a plain Confeſſion, that either our Writers of <hi>Controverſie</hi> are groſly <hi>ignorant,</hi> and know not which are <hi>genuine,</hi> and which are <hi>counterfeit</hi> Authors, or very diſhoneſt, if they do know them, and yet uſe them, and impoſe them upon the World, and that the points in difference can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not otherwiſe, on our ſide, be defended?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Query</hi> XI. Whether the <hi>Pope</hi>'s pretenſions to <hi>Infallibility and Supremacy,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being a means to obtain and preſerve <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> is not one of the greateſt <hi>Impediments and Obſtacles,</hi> that ever ſtood in the way of the <hi>Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church? And alſo are not theſe pretenſions of the Pope, the true <hi>Root and Cauſe</hi> of all the <hi>Schriſms, Wars, Bloudy Maſſacres,</hi> acted by our people upon the poor <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the <hi>Miſeries and Confuſions</hi> that have been in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> in this and other Countries for theſe many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years? And whether, according to all <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>rational</hi> Probability, we might not far ſooner hope, to ſee <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Concord, Peace and Love</hi> in the Church <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and between one <hi>National</hi> Church, and one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> man and another, if this great <hi>Block of Offence</hi> were remov'd? And in a word, Whether there can be any <hi>rational</hi> hopes of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity or Peace,</hi> either in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> till the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is deſtroy'd, and the <hi>Pope</hi> reduced both to the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of a <hi>Primitive Biſhop of Rome?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, <hi>Reverend Fathers,</hi> I am come to the intended limits, and a <hi>concluſion</hi> of my <hi>Letter,</hi> before I have near finiſh'd my <hi>Enquiries.</hi> For a multitude of other troubleſome <hi>Thoughts, Doubts, and Scruples,</hi> in very important matters, crowd in upon me, and preſs for room here. But I muſt bear with their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, till a fairer occaſion. It may be they ſhall be the ſubject of a <hi>Second Letter of Enquiry.</hi> But I humbly beg you to give me a ſpeedy Anſwer to <hi>this.</hi> For pray conſider, how uneaſie 'tis to dwell with a <hi>diſſatisfied Conſcience!</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, I muſt needs tell you, that ſince your <hi>great Prudence</hi> has thought it for the advantage of our Church and Cauſe (which nevertheleſs ſome wiſe men wonder how you could) to publiſh in the Vulgar Tongue our <hi>Canons,</hi> &amp;c. and the <hi>Catechiſm</hi> of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and that I am now convinc'd <hi>Ignorance</hi> is not ſuch a rare and commendable <hi>Virtue,</hi> nor ſo great a Friend to <hi>Devotion,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100283:25"/>as ſome of you have endeavour'd to make me and others believe; I ſay, I am now reſolv'd, not only diligently to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d over theſe <hi>Canons,</hi> &amp;c. but alſo our <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s <hi>Pieces</hi> and the <hi>Anſwers</hi> to them, and alſo as many as I can, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the beſt eſteem'd Books of <hi>Controverſie,</hi> writ by both <hi>Churches.</hi> For I now think it both a moſt <hi>unjust</hi> and <hi>fooliſh</hi> method and courſe to read <hi>only</hi> the Books of the ſide. If Judges ſhould do ſo, what mad Juſtice ſhould we have? And is our <hi>Eternal</hi> Happineſs of leſs concern than worldly matters? But to conclude: I hape, Reverend <hi>Fathers,</hi> nothing has dropt from my Pen, for which I need beg your Pardon; but if there ſhould, I doubt not but your great Charity will give it the moſt favourable <hi>conſtruction,</hi> and excuſe it. Much leſs need I <hi>apologize</hi> that I have not writ this <hi>Letter,</hi> and made my <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries</hi> in an exact <hi>method</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> and like a <hi>Scholar</hi> and an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> ſince you know I pretend to be none. If I have deliver'd my Thoughts ſo <hi>plain and clear,</hi> as to be well underſtood by my unlearned Brethren, and that they are edify'd by them, I have gain'd my ends, and what I paſſionately deſire. But indeed I muſt needs confeſs, that if I had had all the Qualifications of a perfect <hi>Scholar,</hi> I believe I ſhould have proceeded in the ſame manner. For I look upon a <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>inartificial</hi> Dreſs, the moſt agreeable to <hi>Truth and Honeſty.</hi> And as far as theſe permit me, I am,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reverend Fathers,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Servant, <hi>A. B.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>September</hi> the 21th, and <hi>St. Matthew</hi>'s day, 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100283:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
